hi everyone
today we are continuing our
implementation of makemore
now in the last lecture we implemented
the bigram language model and we
implemented it both using counts and
also using a super simple neural network
that had a single linear layer
now this is the
jupyter notebook that we built out last
lecture
and we saw that the way we approached
this is that we looked at only the
single previous character and we
predicted the distribution for the
character that would go next in the
sequence and we did that by taking
counts and normalizing them into
probabilities
so that each row here sums to one
now this is all well and good if you
only have one character of previous
context
and this works and it's approachable the
problem with this model of course is
that
the predictions from this model are not
very good because you only take one
character of context so the model didn't
produce very name like sounding things
now the problem with this approach
though is that if we are to take more
context into account when predicting the
next character in a sequence things
quickly blow up and this table the size
of this table grows and in fact it grows
exponentially with the length of the
context
because if we only take a single
character at a time that's 27
possibilities of context
but if we take two characters in the
past and try to predict the third one
suddenly the number of rows in this
matrix you can look at it that way
is 27 times 27 so there's 729
possibilities for what could have come
in the context
if we take three characters as the
context suddenly we have
20 000 possibilities of context
and so there's just way too many rows of
this matrix it's way too few counts
for each possibility and the whole thing
just kind of explodes and doesn't work
very well
so that's why today we're going to move
on to this bullet point here and we're
going to implement a multi-layer
perceptron model to predict the next uh
character in a sequence
and this modeling approach that we're
going to adopt follows this paper
benguetal 2003
so i have the paper pulled up here
now this isn't the very first paper that
proposed the use of multiglio
perceptrons or neural networks to
predict the next character or token in a
sequence but it's definitely one that is
uh was very influential around that time
it is very often cited to stand in for
this idea and i think it's a very nice
write-up and so this is the paper that
we're going to first look at and then
implement now this paper has 19 pages so
we don't have time to go into
the full detail of this paper but i
invite you to read it
it's very readable interesting and has a
lot of interesting ideas in it as well
in the introduction they describe the
exact same problem i just described and
then to address it they propose the
following model
now keep in mind that we are building a
character level language model so we're
working on the level of characters in
this paper they have a vocabulary of 17
000 possible words and they instead
build a word level language model but
we're going to still stick with the
characters but we'll take the same
modeling approach
now what they do is basically they
propose to take every one of these words
seventeen thousand words and they're
going to associate to each word a say
thirty dimensional feature vector
so every word is now
embedded into a thirty dimensional space
you can think of it that way so we have
17 000 points or vectors in a 30
dimensional space
and that's um you might imagine that's
very crowded that's a lot of points for
a very small space
now
in the beginning these words are
initialized completely randomly so
they're spread out at random
but then we're going to tune these
embeddings of these words using back
propagation
so during the course of training of this
neural network these points or vectors
are going to basically move around in
this space and you might imagine that
for example words that have very similar
meanings or that are indeed synonyms of
each other might end up in a very
similar part of the space and conversely
words that mean very different things
would go somewhere else in a space
now their modeling approach otherwise is
identical to ours they are using a
multi-layer neural network to predict
the next word given the previous words
and to train the neural network they are
maximizing the log likelihood of the
training data just like we did
so the modeling approach itself is
identical now here they have a concrete
example of this intuition
why does it work
basically suppose that for example you
are trying to predict a dog was running
in a blank
now suppose that the exact phrase a dog
was running in a
has never occurred in a training data
and here you are at sort of test time
later when the model is deployed
somewhere
and it's trying to make a sentence and
it's saying a dog was running in a blank
and because it's never encountered this
exact phrase in the training set you're
out of distribution as we say like you
don't have fundamentally any
reason to suspect
what might come next
but this approach actually allows you to
get around that because maybe you didn't
see the exact phrase a dog was running
in a something but maybe you've seen
similar phrases maybe you've seen the
phrase the dog was running in a blank
and maybe your network has learned that
a and the
are like frequently are interchangeable
with each other and so maybe it took the
embedding for a and the embedding for
the and it actually put them like nearby
each other in the space and so you can
transfer knowledge through that
embedding and you can generalize in that
way
similarly the network could know that
cats and dogs are animals and they
co-occur in lots of very similar
contexts and so even though you haven't
seen this exact phrase
or if you haven't seen exactly walking
or running
you can through the embedding space
transfer knowledge and you can
generalize to novel scenarios
so let's now scroll down to the diagram
of the neural network
they have a nice diagram here
and in this example we are taking three
previous words
and we are trying to predict the fourth
word
in a sequence
now these three previous words as i
mentioned uh we have a vocabulary of 17
000 um possible words
so every one of these
basically basically
are the index of the incoming word
and because there are 17 000 words this
is an integer between 0 and 16999
now there's also a lookup table that
they call c
this lookup table is a matrix that is 17
000 by say 30.
and basically what we're doing here is
we're treating this as a lookup table
and so every index is
plucking out a row of this embedding
matrix
so that each index is converted to the
30 dimensional vector that corresponds
to the embedding vector for that word
so here we have the input layer of 30
neurons for three words making up 90
neurons in total
and here they're saying that this matrix
c is shared across all the words so
we're always indexing into the same
matrix c over and over um
for each one of these
words next up is the hidden layer of
this neural network the size of this
hidden neural layer of this neural net
is a hoppy parameter so we use the word
hyperparameter when it's kind of like a
design choice up to the designer of the
neural net and this can be as large as
you'd like or as small as you'd like so
for example the size could be a hundred
and we are going to go over multiple
choices of the size of this hidden layer
and we're going to evaluate how well
they work
so say there were 100 neurons here all
of them would be fully connected to the
90 words or 90 um
numbers that make up these three words
so this is a fully connected layer
then there's a 10 inch long linearity
and then there's this output layer and
because there are 17 000 possible words
that could come next
this layer has 17 000 neurons
and all of them are fully connected to
all of these neurons in the hidden layer
so there's a lot of parameters here
because there's a lot of words so most
computation is here this is the
expensive layer
now there are 17 000 logits here so on
top of there we have the softmax layer
which we've seen in our previous video
as well so every one of these logits is
exponentiated and then everything is
normalized to sum to 1 so that we have a
nice probability distribution for the
next word in the sequence
now of course during training we
actually have the label we have the
identity of the next word in a sequence
that word
or its index is used to pluck out the
probability of that word
and then we are maximizing the
with respect to the parameters of this
neural net
so the parameters are the weights and
biases of this output layer
the weights and biases of the hidden
layer and the embedding lookup table c
and all of that is optimized using back
propagation
and these uh dashed arrows ignore those
uh that represents a variation of a
neural nut that we are not going to
explore in this video
so that's the setup and now let's
implement it
okay so i started a brand new notebook
for this lecture
we are importing pytorch and we are
importing matplotlib so we can create
figures
then i am reading all the names into a
list of words like i did before and i'm
showing the first eight right here
keep in mind that we have a 32 000 in
total these are just the first eight
and then here i'm building out the
vocabulary of characters and all the
mappings from the characters as strings
to integers and vice versa
now the first thing we want to do is we
want to compile the data set for the
neural network
and i had to rewrite this code um i'll
show you in a second what it looks like
so this is the code that i created for
the dataset creation so let me first run
it and then i'll briefly explain how
this works
so first we're going to define something
called block size and this is basically
the context length of how many
characters do we take to predict the
next one so here in this example we're
taking three characters to predict the
fourth one so we have a block size of
three that's the size of the block that
supports the prediction
then here i'm building out the x and y
the x are the input to the neural net
and the y are the labels for each
example inside x
then i'm airing over the first five
words i'm doing first five just for
efficiency while we are developing all
the code but then later we're going to
come here and erase this so that we use
the entire training set
so here i'm printing the word
emma and here i'm basically showing the
examples that we can generate the five
examples that we can generate out of the
single
um sort of word emma
so
when we are given the context of just uh
dot dot the first character in a
sequence is e
in this context the label is m
when the context is this the label is m
and so forth and so the way i build this
out is first i start with a padded
context of just zero tokens
then i iterate over all the characters i
get the character in the sequence and i
basically build out the array y of this
current character and the array x which
stores the current running context
and then here see i print everything and
here i um crop the context and enter the
new character in a sequence so this is
kind of like a rolling window of context
now we can change the block size here to
for example four
and in that case we'll be predicting the
fifth character given the previous four
or it can be five
and then it would look like this
or it can be say ten
and then it would look something like
this we're taking ten characters to
predict the eleventh one
and we're always padding with dots
so let me bring this back to three
just so that we have what we have here
in the paper
and finally the data set right now looks
as follows
from these five words we have created a
data set of 32 examples
and each input of the neural net is
three integers and we have a label that
is also an integer
y
so x looks like this
these are the individual examples
and then y are the labels
so
given this
let's now write a neural network that
takes these axes and predicts the y's
first let's build the embedding lookup
table c
so we have 27 possible characters and
we're going to embed them in a lower
dimensional space
in the paper they have 17 000 words and
they bet them in uh spaces as small
dimensional as 30. so they cram 17 000
words into 30 dimensional space in our
case we have only 27 possible characters
so let's grab them in something as small
as to start with for example a
two-dimensional space
so this lookup table will be random
numbers
and we'll have 27 rows and we'll have
two columns
right so each 20 each one of 27
characters will have a two-dimensional
embedding
so that's our matrix c of embeddings in
the beginning initialized randomly
now before we embed all of the integers
inside the input x using this lookup
table c
let me actually just try to embed a
single individual integer like say five
so we get a sense of how this works
now
one way this works of course is we can
just take the c and we can index into
row five
and that gives us a vector the fifth row
of c
and um
this is one way to do it
the other way that i presented in the
previous lecture is actually seemingly
different but actually identical so in
the previous lecture what we did is we
took these integers and we used the one
hot encoding to first encode them so f.1
hot
we want to encode integer 5 and we want
to tell it that the number of classes is
27 so that's the 26 dimensional vector
of all zeros except the fifth bit is
turned on
now this actually doesn't work
the reason is that
this input actually must be a doorstop
tensor
and i'm making some of these errors
intentionally just so you get to see
some errors and how to fix them
so this must be a tester not an int
fairly straightforward to fix we get a
one hot vector the fifth dimension is
one and the shape of this is 27.
and now notice that just as i briefly
alluded to in the previous video if we
take this one hot vector and we multiply
it by c
then
what would you expect
well number one
first you'd expect an error
because
expected scalar type long but found
float
so a little bit confusing but
the problem here is that one hot the
data type of it
is
long it's a 64-bit integer but this is a
float tensor and so pytorch doesn't know
how to multiply an int with a float and
that's why we had to explicitly cast
this to a float so that we can multiply
now the output actually here
is identical
and that it's identical because of the
way the matrix multiplication here works
we have the one hot um vector
multiplying columns of c
and because of all the zeros they
actually end up masking out everything
in c except for the fifth row which is
plucked out
and so we actually arrive at the same
result
and that tells you that
here we can interpret this first
piece here this embedding of the integer
we can either think of it as the integer
indexing into a lookup table c but
equivalently we can also think of this
little piece here as a first layer of
this bigger neural net
this layer here has neurons that have no
non-linearity there's no 10h they're
just linear neurons and their weight
matrix is c
and then we are encoding integers into
one hot and feeding those into a neural
net and this first layer basically
embeds them
so those are two equivalent ways of
doing the same thing we're just going to
index because it's much much faster and
we're going to discard this
interpretation of one hot inputs into
neural nets and we're just going to
index integers and create and use
embedding tables now embedding a single
integer like 5 is easy enough we can
simply ask pytorch to retrieve the fifth
row of c
or the row index five of c
but how do we simultaneously embed all
of these 32 by three integers stored in
array x
luckily pytorch indexing is fairly
flexible and quite powerful
so it doesn't just work to
ask for a single element five like this
you can actually index using lists so
for example we can get the rows five six
and seven
and this will just work like this we can
index with a list
it doesn't just have to be a list it can
also be a actually a tensor of integers
and we can index with that
so this is a integer tensor 567 and this
will just work as well
in fact we can also for example repeat
row 7 and retrieve it multiple times
and
that same index will just get embedded
multiple times here
so here we are indexing with a
one-dimensional
tensor of integers but it turns out that
you can also index with
multi-dimensional tensors of integers
here we have a two-dimensional in tensor
of integers so we can simply just do c
at x and this just works
and the shape of this
is
32 by 3 which is the original shape and
now for every one of those 32 by 3
integers we've retrieved the embedding
vector
here so basically we have that as an
example
the 13th or example index 13
the second dimension is the integer 1 as
an example
and so
here if we do c of x which gives us that
array and then we index into 13 by two
of that array
then we we get the embedding
here
and you can verify that
c
at one which is the integer at that
location is indeed equal to this
you see they're equal
so basically long story short pytorch
indexing is awesome and to embed
simultaneously all of the integers in x
we can simply do c of x
and that is our embedding
and that just works
now let's construct this layer here the
hidden layer
so we have that w1 as i'll call it are
these weights which we will initialize
randomly
now the number of inputs to this layer
is going to be
three times two right because we have
two dimensional embeddings and we have
three of them
so the number of inputs is 6
and the number of neurons in this layer
is a variable up to us
let's use 100 neurons as an example
and then biases
will be also initialized randomly as an
example
and let's and we just need 100 of them
now the problem with this is we can't
simply normally we would take the input
in this case that's embedding and we'd
like to multiply it with these weights
and then we would like to add the bias
this is roughly what we want to do
but the problem here is that these
embeddings are stacked up in the
dimensions of this input tensor
so this will not work this matrix
multiplication because this is a shape
32 by 3 by 2 and i can't multiply that
by 6 by 100
so somehow we need to concatenate these
inputs here together so that we can do
something along these lines which
currently does not work
so how do we transform this 32 by 3 by 2
into a 32 by 6 so that we can actually
perform
this
multiplication over here i'd like to
show you that there are usually many
ways of
implementing what you'd like to do in
torch and some of them will be faster
better shorter etc
and that's because torch is a very large
library and it's got lots and lots of
functions so if you just go to the
documentation and click on torch you'll
see that my slider here is very tiny and
that's because there are so many
functions that you can call on these
tensors
to transform them create them multiply
them add them perform all kinds of
different operations on them
and so this is kind of like
the space of possibility if you will
now one of the things that you can do is
if we can control here ctrl f for
concatenate and we see that there's a
function
torque.cat short for concatenate
and this concatenates the given sequence
of tensors in a given dimension
and these sensors must have the same
shape etc so we can use the concatenate
operation to in a naive way concatenate
these three embeddings for each input
so in this case we have m of
amp of the shape and really what we want
to do is we want to retrieve these three
parts and concatenate them
so we want to grab all the examples
we want to grab
first the zeroth
index
and then all of
this
so this plucks out
the 32 by 2 embeddings of just the first
word here
and so basically we want this guy
we want the first dimension and we want
the second dimension
and these are the three pieces
individually
and then we want to treat this as a
sequence and we want to torch that cat
on that sequence so this is the list
tor.cat takes a
sequence
of tensors and then we have to tell it
along which dimension to concatenate
so in this case all these are 32 by 2
and we want to concatenate not across
dimension 0 by the cross dimension one
so passing in one
gives us a result
the shape of this is 32 by 6 exactly as
we'd like
so that basically took 32 and squashed
these by concatenating them into 32 by
6.
now this is kind of ugly because this
code would not generalize if we want to
later change the block size right now we
have three inputs
three words but what if we had five
then here we would have to change the
code because i'm indexing directly well
torch comes to rescue again because that
turns out to be a function called unbind
and it removes a tensor dimension
so it removes the tensor dimension
returns a tuple of all slices along a
given dimension
without it
so this is exactly what we need
and basically when we call torch dot
unbind
torch dot unbind
of m
and pass in dimension
1 index 1
this gives us a list of
a list of tensors exactly equivalent to
this
so running this
gives us a line
and it's exactly this list and so we can
call torch.cat on it
and along the first dimension
and this works
and this shape is the same
but now this is uh it doesn't matter if
we have block size 3 or 5 or 10 this
will just work
so this is one way to do it but it turns
out that in this case there's actually a
significantly better and more efficient
way and this gives me an opportunity to
hint at some of the internals of
torch.tensor
so let's create
an array here
of elements from 0 to 17
and the shape of this
is just 18. it's a single picture of 18
numbers
it turns out that we can very quickly
re-represent this as different sized and
dimensional tensors
we do this by calling a view
and we can say that actually this is not
a single vector of 18 this is a two by
nine tensor or alternatively this is a
nine by two tensor
or this is actually a three by three by
two tensor
as long as the total number of elements
here multiply to be the same
this will just work and
in pytorch this operation calling that
view is extremely efficient
and the reason for that is that
in each tensor there's something called
the underlying storage
and the storage is just the numbers
always as a one-dimensional vector and
this is how this tensor is represented
in the computer memory it's always a
one-dimensional vector
but when we call that view we are
manipulating some of attributes of that
tensor that dictate how this
one-dimensional sequence is interpreted
to be an n-dimensional tensor
and so what's happening here is that no
memory is being changed copied moved or
created when we call that view the
storage
is identical but when you call that view
some of the internal
attributes of the view of the sensor are
being manipulated and changed in
particular that's something there's
something called a storage offset
strides and shapes and those are
manipulated so that this one-dimensional
sequence of bytes is seen as different
and dimensional arrays
there's a blog post here from eric
called pi torch internals where he goes
into some of this with respect to tensor
and how the view of the tensor is
represented
and this is really just like a logical
construct of representing the physical
memory
and so this is a pretty good um blog
post that you can go into i might also
create an entire video on the internals
of torch tensor and how this works
for here we just note that this is an
extremely efficient operation
and if i delete this and come back to
our end
we see that the shape of our end is 32
by three by two but we can simply
ask for pytorch to view this instead as
a 32 by six
and the way this gets flattened into a
32 by six array
just happens that
these two
get stacked up
in a single row and so that's basically
the concatenation operation that we're
after
and you can verify that this actually
gives the exact same result as what we
had before
so this is an element y equals and you
can see that all the elements of these
two tensors are the same
and so we get the exact same result
so long story short we can actually just
come here
and if we just view this as a 32x6
instead then this multiplication will
work and give us the hidden states that
we're after
so if this is h
then h shape is now
the 100 dimensional activations for
every one of our 32 examples
and this gives the desired result let me
do two things here number one let's not
use 32 we can for example do something
like
m.shape at 0
so that we don't hard code these numbers
and this would work for any size of this
amp
or alternatively we can also do negative
one when we do negative one pi torch
will infer what this should be
because the number of elements must be
the same and we're saying that this is 6
by church will derive that this must be
32 or whatever else it is if m is of
different size
the other thing is here um
one more thing i'd like to point out is
here when we do the concatenation
this actually is much less efficient
because um this concatenation would
create a whole new tensor with a whole
new storage so new memory is being
created because there's no way to
concatenate tensors just by manipulating
the view attributes
so this is inefficient and creates all
kinds of new memory
uh so let me delete this now
we don't need this
and here to calculate h we want to also
dot 10h
of this
to get our
oops to get our h
so these are now numbers between
negative one and one because of the 10h
and we have
that the shape is 32 by 100
and that is basically this hidden layer
of activations here
for every one of our 32 examples
now there's one more thing i've lost
over that we have to be very careful
with and that this
and that's this plus here
in particular we want to make sure that
the broadcasting will do what we like
the shape of this is 32 by 100 and the
ones shape is 100.
so we see that the addition here will
broadcast these two and in particular we
have 32 by 100 broadcasting to 100.
so broadcasting will align on the right
create a fake dimension here so this
will become a 1 by 100 row vector and
then it will copy vertically
for every one of these rows of 32 and do
an element wise addition
so in this case the correct thing will
be happening because the same bias
vector will be added to all the rows
of
this matrix so that is correct that's
what we'd like and it's always good
practice you just make sure
so that you don't shoot yourself in the
foot and finally let's create the final
layer here
so let's create
w2 and v2
the input now is 100
and the output number of neurons will be
for us 27 because we have 27 possible
characters that come next
so the biases will be 27 as well
so therefore the logits which are the
outputs of this neural net
are going to be um
h
multiplied by w2 plus b2
logistic shape is 32 by 27
and the logits look
good now exactly as we saw in the
previous video we want to take these
logits and we want to first exponentiate
them to get our fake counts
and then we want to normalize them into
a probability
so prob is counts divide
and now
counts dot sum along the first dimension
and keep them as true exactly as in the
previous video
and so
prob that shape now is 32 by 27
and you'll see that every row of prob
sums to one so it's normalized
so that gives us the probabilities now
of course we have the actual letter that
comes next and that comes from this
array y
which we which we created during the
dataset creation so why is this last
piece here which is the identity of the
next character in the sequence that we'd
like to now predict
so what we'd like to do now is just as
in the previous video we'd like to index
into the rows of prob and in each row
we'd like to pluck out the probability
assigned to the correct character
as given here
so first we have torch.range of 32 which
is kind of like a iterator over
numbers from 0 to 31
and then we can index into prob in the
following way
prop in
torch.range of 32 which iterates the
roads and in each row we'd like to grab
this column as given by y
so this gives the current probabilities
as assigned by this neural network with
this setting of its weights
to the correct character in the sequence
and you can see here that this looks
okay for some of these characters like
this is basically 0.2
but it doesn't look very good at all for
many other characters like this is
0.0701 probability and so the network
thinks that some of these are extremely
unlikely but of course we haven't
trained the neural network yet so
this will improve and ideally all of
these numbers here of course are one
because then we are correctly predicting
the next character
now just as in the previous video we
want to take these probabilities we want
to look at the lock probability
and then we want to look at the average
probability
and the negative of it to create the
negative log likelihood loss
so the loss here is 17
and this is the loss that we'd like to
minimize to get the network to predict
the correct character in the sequence
okay so i rewrote everything here and
made it a bit more respectable so here's
our data set here's all the parameters
that we defined
i'm now using a generator to make it
reproducible
i clustered all the parameters into a
single list of parameters so that for
example it's easy to count them and see
that in total we currently have about
3400 parameters
and this is the forward pass as we
developed it
and we arrive at a single number here
the loss that is currently expressing
how well
this neural network works with the
current setting of parameters
now i would like to make it even more
respectable so in particular see these
lines here where we take the logits and
we calculate the loss
we're not actually reinventing the wheel
here this is just um
classification and many people use
classification and that's why there is a
functional.cross entropy function in
pytorch to calculate this much more
efficiently
so we can just simply call f.cross
entropy
and we can pass in the logits and we can
pass in the
array of targets y
and this calculates the exact same loss
so in fact we can simply put this here
and erase these three lines and we're
going to get the exact same result now
there are actually many good reasons to
prefer f.cross entropy over rolling your
own implementation like this i did this
for educational reasons but you'd never
use this in practice why is that
number one when you use f.cross entropy
by torch will not actually create all
these intermediate tensors because these
are all new tensors in memory and all
this is fairly inefficient to run like
this instead pytorch will cluster up all
these operations and very often create
have fused kernels that very efficiently
evaluate these expressions that are sort
of like clustered mathematical
operations
number two the backward pass can be made
much more efficient and not just because
it's a fused kernel but also
analytically and mathematically it's
much it's often a very much simpler
backward pass to implement
we actually sell this with micrograd
you see here when we implemented 10h the
forward pass of this operation to
calculate the 10h was actually a fairly
complicated mathematical expression
but because it's a clustered
mathematical expression when we did the
backward pass we didn't individually
backward through the x and the two times
and the minus one in division etc we
just said it's one minus t squared and
that's a much simpler mathematical
expression
and we were able to do this because
we're able to reuse calculations and
because we are able to mathematically
and analytically derive the derivative
and often that expression simplifies
mathematically and so there's much less
to implement
so not only can can it be made more
efficient because it runs in a fused
kernel but also because the expressions
can take a much simpler form
mathematically
so that's number one number two
under the hood f that cross entropy can
also be significantly more um
numerically well behaved let me show you
an example of how this works
suppose we have a logits of negative 2 3
negative 3 0 and 5
and then we are taking the exponent of
it and normalizing it to sum to 1.
so
when logits take on this values
everything is well and good and we get a
nice probability distribution
now consider what happens when some of
these logits take on more extreme values
and that can happen during optimization
of the neural network
suppose that some of these numbers grow
very negative like say negative 100
then actually everything will come out
fine we still get the probabilities that
um
you know are well behaved and they sum
to one and everything is great
but because of the way the x works if
you have very positive logits let's say
positive 100 in here
you actually start to run into trouble
and we get not a number here
and the reason for that is that these
counts
have an if here
so if you pass in a very negative number
to x you just get a very negative sorry
not negative but very small number very
very near zero and that's fine
but if you pass in a very positive
number suddenly we run out of range in
our floating point number that
represents these counts
so basically we're taking e and we're
raising it to the power of 100 and that
gives us if because we run out of
dynamic range on this floating point
number that is count
and so we cannot pass very large logits
through this expression
now let me reset these numbers to
something reasonable
the way pi torch solved this
is that
you see how we have a well-behaved
result here
it turns out that because of the
normalization here you can actually
offset logits by any arbitrary constant
value that you want so if i add 1 here
you actually get the exact same result
or if i add 2
or if i subtract three
any offset will produce the exact same
probabilities
so because negative numbers are okay but
positive numbers can actually overflow
this x what patrick does is it
internally calculates the maximum value
that occurs in the logits and it
subtracts it so in this case it would
subtract five
and so therefore the greatest number in
logits will become zero and all the
other numbers will become some negative
numbers
and then the result of this is always
well behaved so even if we have 100 here
previously
not good but because pytorch will
subtract 100 this will work
and so there's many good reasons to call
cross-entropy number one the forward
pass can be much more efficient the
backward pass can be much more efficient
and also things can be much more
numerically well behaved okay so let's
now set up the training of this neural
net
we have the forward pass
uh we don't need these
is that we have the losses equal to the
f.cross entropy that's the forward pass
then we need the backward pass first we
want to set the gradients to be zero so
for p in parameters
we want to make sure that p dot grad is
none which is the same as setting it to
zero in pi torch
and then lost that backward to populate
those gradients
once we have the gradients we can do the
parameter update so for p in parameters
we want to take all the
data and we want to nudge it
learning rate times p dot grad
and then we want to repeat this
a few times
and let's print the loss here as well
now this won't suffice and it will
create an error because we also have to
go for pn parameters
and we have to make sure that p dot
requires grad is set to true in pi torch
and this should just work
okay so we started off with loss of 17
and we're decreasing it
let's run longer
and you see how the loss decreases
a lot here so
if we just run for a thousand times
we get a very very low loss and that
means that we're making very good
predictions now the reason that this is
so straightforward right now
is because we're only um
overfitting 32 examples
so we only have 32 examples uh of the
first five words
and therefore it's very easy to make
this neural net fit only these two 32
examples because we have 3 400
parameters and only 32 examples so we're
doing what's called overfitting a single
batch of the data
and getting a very low loss and good
predictions
um but that's just because we have so
many parameters for so few examples so
it's easy to
uh make this be very low
now we're not able to achieve exactly
zero
and the reason for that is we can for
example look at logits which are being
predicted
and we can look at the max along the
first dimension
and in pi torch
max reports both the actual values that
take on the maximum number but also the
indices of piece
and you'll see that the indices are very
close to the labels
but in some cases they differ
for example in this very first example
the predicted index is 19 but the label
is five
and we're not able to make loss be zero
and fundamentally that's because here
the very first or the zeroth index is
the example where dot dot dot is
supposed to predict e but you see how
dot dot dot is also supposed to predict
an o and dot dot is also supposed to
predict an i and then s as well and so
basically e o a or s are all possible
outcomes in a training set for the exact
same input so we're not able to
completely over fit and um
and make the loss be exactly zero so but
we're getting very close in the cases
where
there's a unique input for a unique
output in those cases we do what's
called overfit and we basically get the
exact same and the exact correct result
so now all we have to do
is we just need to make sure that we
read in the full data set and optimize
the neural net
okay so let's swing back up
where we created the dataset
and we see that here we only use the
first five words so let me now erase
this
and let me erase the print statements
otherwise we'd be printing way too much
and so when we processed the full data
set of all the words we now had 228 000
examples instead of just 32.
so let's now scroll back down
to this is much larger reinitialize the
weights the same number of parameters
they all require gradients
and then let's push this print out
lost.item to be here
and let's just see how the optimization
goes if we run this
okay so we started with a fairly high
loss and then as we're optimizing the
loss is coming down
but you'll notice that it takes quite a
bit of time for every single iteration
so let's actually address that because
we're doing way too much work forwarding
and backwarding 220 000 examples
in practice what people usually do is
they perform forward and backward pass
and update on many batches of the data
so what we will want to do is we want to
randomly select some portion of the data
set and that's a mini batch and then
only forward backward and update on that
little mini batch and then
we iterate on those many batches
so in pytorch we can for example use
storage.randint
we can generate numbers between 0 and 5
and make 32 of them
i believe the size has to be a
tuple
in my torch
so we can have a tuple 32 of numbers
between zero and five but actually we
want x dot shape of zero here
and so this creates uh integers that
index into our data set and there's 32
of them so if our mini batch size is 32
then we can come here and we can first
do a mini batch
construct
so in the integers that we want to
optimize in this
single iteration
are in the ix
and then we want to index into
x
with ix to only grab those rows
so we're only getting 32 rows of x
and therefore embeddings will again be
32 by three by two not two hundred
thousand by three by two
and then this ix has to be used not just
to index into x
but also to index into y
and now this should be many batches and
this should be much much faster so
okay so it's instant almost
so this way we can run many many
examples
nearly instantly and decrease the loss
much much faster
now because we're only dealing with mini
batches the quality of our gradient is
lower so the direction is not as
reliable it's not the actual gradient
direction
but the gradient direction is good
enough even when it's estimating on only
32 examples that it is useful and so
it's much better to have an approximate
gradient and just make more steps than
it is to evaluate the exact gradient and
take fewer steps so that's why in
practice uh this works quite well
so let's now continue the optimization
let me take out this lost item from here
and uh
place it over here at the end
okay so we're hovering around 2.5 or so
however this is only the loss for that
mini batch so let's actually evaluate
the loss
here
for all of x
and for all of y just so we have a
full sense of exactly how all the model
is doing right now
so right now we're at about 2.7 on the
entire training set
so let's
run the optimization for a while
okay right 2.6
2.57
2.53
okay
so one issue of course is we don't know
if we're stepping too slow or too fast
so this point one i just guessed it
so one question is how do you determine
this learning rate
and how do we gain confidence that we're
stepping in the right
sort of speed so i'll show you one way
to determine a reasonable learning rate
it works as follows let's reset our
parameters
to the initial
settings
and now let's
print in every step
but let's only do 10 steps or so
or maybe maybe 100 steps
we want to find like a very reasonable
set
search range if you will so for example
if this is like very low
then
we see that the loss is barely
decreasing so that's not
that's like too low basically so let's
try
this one
okay so we're decreasing the loss but
like not very quickly so that's a pretty
good low range
now let's reset it again
and now let's try to find the place at
which the loss kind of explodes
uh so maybe at negative one
okay we see that we're minimizing the
loss but you see how uh it's kind of
unstable it goes up and down quite a bit
um so negative one is probably like a
fast learning rate let's try negative
10.
okay so this
isn't optimizing this is not working
very well so negative 10 is way too big
negative one was already kind of big
um
so therefore
negative one was like somewhat
reasonable if i reset
so i'm thinking that the right learning
rate is somewhere between
uh negative zero point zero zero one and
um
negative one
so the way we can do this here is we can
use uh torch shot lens space
and we want to basically do something
like this between zero and one but
um
those number of steps is one more
parameter that's required let's do a
thousand steps this creates 1000
numbers between 0.01 and 1
but it doesn't really make sense to step
between these linearly so instead let me
create learning rate exponent
and instead of 0.001 this will be a
negative 3 and this will be a zero
and then the actual lrs that we want to
search over are going to be 10 to the
power of lre
so now what we're doing is we're
stepping linearly between the exponents
of these learning rates this is 0.001
and this is 1 because 10 to the power of
0 is 1.
and therefore we are spaced
exponentially in this interval
so these are the candidate learning
rates
that we want to sort of like search over
roughly
so now what we're going to do is
here we are going to run the
optimization for 1000 steps
and instead of using a fixed number
we are going to use learning rate
indexing into here lrs of i
and make this i
so basically let me reset this to be
again starting from random
creating these learning rates between
negative
zero points between 0.001 and um
one but exponentially stopped
and here what we're doing is we're
iterating a thousand times
we're going to use the learning rate
um that's in the beginning very very low
in the beginning is going to be 0.001
but by the end it's going to be
1.
and then we're going to step with that
learning rate
and now what we want to do is we want to
keep track of the uh
learning rates that we used and we want
to look at the losses
that resulted
and so here let me
track stats
so lri.append lr
and um lost side that append
loss that item
okay
so again reset everything
and then run
and so basically we started with a very
low learning rate and we went all the
way up to a learning rate of negative
one
and now what we can do is we can plt
that plot
and we can plot the two so we can plot
the learning rates on the x-axis and the
losses we saw on the y-axis
and often you're going to find that your
plot looks something like this
where in the beginning
you had very low learning rates so
basically anything
barely anything happened
then we got to like a nice spot here
and then as we increase the learning
rate enough
we basically started to be kind of
unstable here
so a good learning rate turns out to be
somewhere around here
um and because we have lri here
um
we actually may want to
do not lr
not the learning rate but the exponent
so that would be the lre at i is maybe
what we want to log so let me reset this
and redo that calculation
but now on the x axis we have the
[Music]
exponent of the learning rate and so we
can see the exponent of the learning
rate that is good to use it would be
sort of like roughly in the valley here
because here the learning rates are just
way too low and then here where we
expect relatively good learning rates
somewhere here and then here things are
starting to explode so somewhere around
negative one x the exponent of the
learning rate is a pretty good setting
and 10 to the negative one is 0.1 so 0.1
is actually 0.1 was actually a fairly
good learning rate around here
and that's what we had in the initial
setting
but that's roughly how you would
determine it and so here now we can take
out the tracking of these
and we can just simply set lr to be 10
to the negative one or
basically otherwise 0.1 as it was before
and now we have some confidence that
this is actually a fairly good learning
rate
and so now we can do is we can crank up
the iterations
we can reset our optimization
and
we can run for a pretty long time using
this learning rate
oops and we don't want to print that's
way too much printing
so let me again reset
and run ten thousand stops
okay so we're 0.2 2.48 roughly let's run
another 10 000 steps
2.46
and now let's do one learning rate decay
what this means is we're going to take
our learning rate and we're going to 10x
lower it and so we're at the late stages
of training potentially and we may want
to go a bit slower let's do one more
actually at 0.1 just to see if
we're making a dent here
okay we're still making dent and by the
way the
bi-gram loss that we achieved last video
was 2.45 so we've already surpassed the
bi-gram model
and once i get a sense that this is
actually kind of starting to plateau off
people like to do as i mentioned this
learning rate decay so let's try to
decay the loss
the learning rate i mean
and we achieve it about 2.3 now
obviously this is janky and not exactly
how you would train it in production but
this is roughly what you're going
through you first find a decent learning
rate using the approach that i showed
you
then you start with that learning rate
and you train for a while
and then at the end people like to do a
learning rate decay where you decay the
learning rate by say a factor of 10 and
you do a few more steps and then you get
a trained network roughly speaking
so we've achieved 2.3 and dramatically
improved on the bi-gram language model
using this simple neural net as
described here
using these 3 400 parameters now there's
something we have to be careful with
i said that we have a better model
because we are achieving a lower loss
2.3 much lower than 2.45 with the
bi-gram model previously
now that's not exactly true and the
reason that's not true is that
this is actually fairly small model but
these models can get larger and larger
if you keep adding neurons and
parameters so you can imagine that we
don't potentially have a thousand
parameters we could have 10 000 or 100
000 or millions of parameters
and as the capacity of the neural
network grows
it becomes more and more capable of
overfitting your training set
what that means is that the loss on the
training set on the data that you're
training on will become very very low as
low as zero
but all that the model is doing is
memorizing your training set verbatim so
if you take that model and it looks like
it's working really well but you try to
sample from it you will basically only
get examples exactly as they are in the
training set you won't get any new data
in addition to that if you try to
evaluate the loss on some withheld names
or other words
you will actually see that the loss on
those can be very high and so basically
it's not a good model
so the standard in the field is to split
up your data set into three splits as we
call them we have the training split the
dev split or the validation split
and the test split
so
training split
test or um sorry dev or validation split
and test split and typically this would
be say eighty percent of your data set
this could be ten percent and this ten
percent roughly
so you have these three splits of the
data
now these eighty percent of your
trainings of the data set the training
set is used to optimize the parameters
of the model just like we're doing here
using gradient descent
these 10 percent of the
examples the dev or validation split
they're used for development over all
the hyper parameters of your model so
hyper parameters are for example the
size of this hidden layer
the size of the embedding so this is a
hundred or a two for us but we could try
different things
the strength of the regularization which
we aren't using yet so far
so there's lots of different hybrid
parameters and settings that go into
defining your neural net and you can try
many different variations of them and
see whichever one works best on your
validation split
so this is used to train the parameters
this is used to train the hyperprimers
and test split is used to evaluate
basically the performance of the model
at the end
so we're only evaluating the loss on the
test plate very very sparingly and very
few times because every single time you
evaluate your test loss and you learn
something from it
you are basically starting to also train
on the test split
so you are only allowed to test the loss
on a test
set
very very few times otherwise you risk
overfitting to it as well as you
experiment on your model
so let's also split up our training data
into train dev and test and then we are
going to train on train
and only evaluate on tests very very
sparingly okay so here we go
here is where we took all the words and
put them into x and y tensors
so instead let me create a new cell here
and let me just copy paste some code
here
because i don't think it's that
complex but
we're going to try to save a little bit
of time
i'm converting this to be a function now
and this function takes some list of
words and builds the arrays x and y for
those words only
and then here i am shuffling up all the
words so these are the input words that
we get
we are randomly shuffling them all up
and then um
we're going to
set n1 to be
the number of examples that there's 80
of the words and n2 to be
of the way of the words so basically if
len of words is 32 000 n1 is
well sorry i should probably run this
n1 is 25 000 and n2 is 28 000.
and so here we see that
i'm calling build data set to build the
training set x and y
by indexing into up to and one so we're
going to have only 25 000 training words
and then we're going to have
roughly
n2 minus n1
3 3 000 validation examples or dev
examples and we're going to have
when of words basically minus and two
or
3 204 examples
here for the test set
so
now we have x's and y's
for all those three splits
oh yeah i'm printing their size here
inside the function as well
but here we don't have words but these
are already the individual examples made
from those words
so let's now scroll down here
and the data set now for training is
more like this
and then when we reset the network
when we're training we're only going to
be training using x train
x train and y train
so that's the only thing we're training
on
let's see where we are on the
single batch
let's now train maybe a few more steps
training neural networks can take a
while usually you don't do it inline you
launch a bunch of jobs and you wait for
them to finish um can take in multiple
days and so on
luckily this is a very small network
okay so the loss is pretty good
oh we accidentally used a learning rate
that is way too low
so let me actually come back
we use the decay learning rate of 0.01
so this will train much faster
and then here when we evaluate
let's use the dep set here
xdev
and ydev to evaluate the loss
okay
and let's now decay the learning rate
and only do say 10 000 examples
and let's evaluate the dev loss
ones here
okay so we're getting about 2.3 on dev
and so the neural network when it was
training did not see these dev examples
it hasn't optimized on them and yet
when we evaluate the loss on these dev
we actually get a pretty decent loss
and so we can also look at what the
loss is on all of training set
oops
and so we see that the training and the
dev loss are about equal so we're not
over fitting
um this model is not powerful enough to
just be purely memorizing the data and
so far we are what's called underfitting
because the training loss and the dev or
test losses are roughly equal so what
that typically means is that our network
is very tiny very small and we expect to
make performance improvements by scaling
up the size of this neural net so let's
do that now so let's come over here
and let's increase the size of the
neural net the easiest way to do this is
we can come here to the hidden layer
which currently has 100 neurons and
let's just bump this up so let's do 300
neurons
and then this is also 300 biases and
here we have 300 inputs into the final
layer
so
let's initialize our neural net we now
have ten thousand ex ten thousand
parameters instead of three thousand
parameters
and then we're not using this
and then here what i'd like to do is i'd
like to actually uh keep track of uh
tap
um
okay let's just do this let's keep stats
again
and here when we're keeping track of the
loss let's just also keep track of the
steps and let's just have i here
and let's train on thirty thousand
or rather say
okay let's try thirty thousand
and we are at point one
and
we should be able to run this
and optimize the neural net
and then here basically i want to
plt.plot
the steps
against the loss
so these are the x's and y's
and this is
the loss function and how it's being
optimized
now you see that there's quite a bit of
thickness to this and that's because we
are optimizing over these mini batches
and the mini batches create a little bit
of noise
in this
uh where are we in the def set we are at
2.5 so we still haven't optimized this
neural net very well
and that's probably because we made it
bigger it might take longer for this
neural net to converge
um
and so let's continue training
yeah let's just continue training
one possibility is that the batch size
is so low
that uh we just have way too much noise
in the training and we may want to
increase the batch size so that we have
a bit more um correct gradient and we're
not thrashing too much and we can
actually like optimize more properly
okay
this will now become meaningless because
we've reinitialized these so
yeah this looks not
pleasing right now but there probably is
like a tiny improvement but it's so hard
to tell
let's go again
2.52
let's try to decrease the learning rate
by factor two
okay we're at 2.32
let's continue training
we basically expect to see a lower loss
than what we had before because now we
have a much much bigger model and we
were under fitting so we'd expect that
increasing the size of the model should
help the neural net
2.32 okay so that's not happening too
well
now one other concern is that even
though we've made the 10h layer here or
the hidden layer much much bigger it
could be that the bottleneck of the
network right now are these embeddings
that are two dimensional it can be that
we're just cramming way too many
characters into just two dimensions and
the neural net is not able to really use
that space effectively and that that is
sort of like the bottleneck to our
network's performance
okay 2.23 so just by decreasing the
learning rate i was able to make quite a
bit of progress let's run this one more
time
and then evaluate the training and the
dev loss
now one more thing after training that
i'd like to do is i'd like to visualize
the um
embedding vectors for these
characters before we scale up the
embedding size from two
because we'd like to make uh this
bottleneck potentially go away
but once i make this greater than two we
won't be able to visualize them
so here
okay we're at 2.23 and 2.24
so um we're not improving much more and
maybe the bottleneck now is the
character embedding size which is two
so here i have a bunch of code that will
create a figure
and then we're going to visualize
the embeddings that were trained by the
neural net
on these characters because right now
the embedding has just two so we can
visualize all the characters with the x
and the y coordinates as the two
embedding locations for each of these
characters
and so here are the x coordinates and
the y coordinates which are the columns
of c
and then for each one i also include the
text of the little character
so here what we see is actually kind of
interesting
the network has basically learned to
separate out the characters and cluster
them a little bit uh so for example you
see how the vowels
a e i o u are clustered up here
so that's telling us that is that the
neural net treats these is very similar
right because when they feed into the
neural net
the embedding uh for all these
characters is very similar and so the
neural net thinks that they're very
similar and kind of like interchangeable
if that makes sense
um
then the the points that are like really
far away are for example q q is kind of
treated as an exception and q has a very
special
embedding vector so to speak
similarly dot which is a special
character is all the way out here
and a lot of the other letters are sort
of like clustered up here and so it's
kind of interesting that there's a
little bit of structure here
after the training
and it's not definitely not random and
these embeddings make sense
so we're now going to scale up the
embedding size and won't be able to
visualize it directly but we expect that
because we're under fitting
and we made this layer much bigger and
did not sufficiently improve the loss
we're thinking that the um
constraint to better performance right
now could be these embedding pictures so
let's make them bigger okay so let's
scroll up here
and now we don't have two dimensional
embeddings we are going to have
say 10 dimensional embeddings for each
word
then
this layer will receive 3 times 10 so 30
inputs
will go into
the hidden layer
let's also make the hidden layer a bit
smaller so instead of 300 let's just do
200 neurons in that hidden layer
so now the total number of elements will
be slightly bigger at 11 000
and then here we have to be a bit
careful because um
okay the learning rate we set to 0.1
here we are hardcoded in six and
obviously if you're working in
production you don't wanna be
hard-coding magic numbers but instead of
six this should now be thirty
um
and let's run for fifty thousand
iterations and let me split out the
initialization here outside
so that when we run this cell multiple
times it's not going to wipe out
our loss
in addition to that
here
let's instead of logging lost.item let's
actually
log the
let's
do log 10
i believe that's a function of the loss
and i'll show you why in a second let's
optimize this
basically i'd like to plot the log loss
instead of the loss because when you
plot the loss many times it can have
this hockey stick appearance and log
squashes it in
uh so it just kind of like looks nicer
so the x-axis is step i
and the y-axis will be the loss i
and then here this is 30.
ideally we wouldn't be hard-coding these
okay so let's look at the loss
okay it's again very thick because the
mini batch size is very small but the
total loss over the training set is 2.3
and the the tests or the def set is 2.38
as well
so so far so good uh let's try to now
decrease the learning rate
by a factor of 10
and train for another 50 000 iterations
we'd hope that we would be able to beat
uh 2.32
but again we're just kind of like doing
this very haphazardly so i don't
actually have confidence that our
learning rate is set very well that our
learning rate decay which we just do
at random is set very well
and um so the optimization here is kind
of suspect to be honest and this is not
how you would do it typically in
production in production you would
create parameters or hyper parameters
out of all these settings and then you
would run lots of experiments and see
whichever ones are working well for you
okay
so we have 2.17 now and 2.2 okay so you
see how the training and the validation
performance are starting to slightly
slowly depart
so maybe we're getting the sense that
the neural net
is getting good enough or
that number of parameters is large
enough that we are slowly starting to
overfit
let's maybe run one more iteration of
this
and see where we get
but yeah basically you would be running
lots of experiments and then you are
slowly scrutinizing whichever ones give
you the best depth performance and then
once you find all the
hyper parameters that make your dev
performance good you take that model and
you evaluate the test set performance a
single time and that's the number that
you report in your paper or wherever
else you want to talk about and brag
about your model
so let's then rerun the plot and rerun
the train and death
and because we're getting lower loss now
it is the case that the embedding size
of these was holding us back very likely
okay so 2.162.19 is what we're roughly
getting
so there's many ways to go from many
ways to go from here we can continue
tuning the optimization
we can continue for example playing with
the sizes of the neural net or we can
increase the number of uh
words or characters in our case that we
are taking as an input so instead of
just three characters we could be taking
more characters as an input and that
could further improve the loss
okay so i changed the code slightly so
we have here 200 000 steps of the
optimization and in the first 100 000
we're using a learning rate of 0.1 and
then in the next 100 000 we're using a
learning rate of 0.01
this is the loss that i achieve
and these are the performance on the
training and validation loss
and in particular the best validation
loss i've been able to obtain in the
last 30 minutes or so is 2.17
so now i invite you to beat this number
and you have quite a few knobs available
to you to i think surpass this number
so number one you can of course change
the number of neurons in the hidden
layer of this model you can change the
dimensionality of the embedding
lookup table
you can change the number of characters
that are feeding in as an input
as the context into this model
and then of course you can change the
details of the optimization how long are
we running what is the learning rate how
does it change over time
how does it decay
you can change the batch size and you
may be able to actually achieve a much
better convergence speed
in terms of
how many seconds or minutes it takes to
train the model and get
your result in terms of really good
loss
and then of course i actually invite you
to read this paper it is 19 pages but at
this point you should actually be able
to read a good chunk of this paper and
understand
pretty good chunks of it
and this paper also has quite a few
ideas for improvements that you can play
with
so all of those are not available to you
and you should be able to beat this
number i'm leaving that as an exercise
to the reader and that's it for now and
i'll see you next time
before we wrap up i also wanted to show
how you would sample from the model
so we're going to generate 20 samples
at first we begin with all dots so
that's the context
and then until we generate
the zeroth character again
we're going to embed the current context
using the embedding table c now usually
uh here the first dimension was the size
of the training set but here we're only
working with a single example that we're
generating so this is just the mission
one just for simplicity
and so this embedding then gets
projected into the end state you get the
logits
now we calculate the probabilities for
that you can use f.softmax
of logits and that just basically
exponentiates the logits and makes them
sum to one and similar to cross entropy
it is careful that there's no overflows
once we have the probabilities we sample
from them using torture multinomial to
get our next index and then we shift the
context window to append the index and
record it and then we can just
decode all the integers to strings
and print them out
and so these are some example samples
and you can see that the model now works
much better so the words here are much
more word like or name like so we have
things like ham
joes
you know it's starting to sound a little
bit more name-like so we're definitely
making progress but we can still improve
on this model quite a lot
okay sorry there's some bonus content i
wanted to mention that i want to make
these notebooks more accessible and so i
don't want you to have to like install
jupyter notebooks and torch and
everything else so i will be sharing a
link to a google colab
and google collab will look like a
notebook in your browser and you can
just go to the url and you'll be able to
execute all of the code that you saw in
the google collab and so this is me
executing the code in this lecture and i
shortened it a little bit but basically
you're able to train the exact same
network and then plot and sample from
the model and everything is ready for
you to like tinker with the numbers
right there in your browser no
installation necessary
so i just wanted to point that out and
the link to this will be in the video
description