hi everyone hope you're well
and next up what i'd like to do is i'd
like to build out make more
like micrograd before it make more is a
repository that i have on my github
webpage
you can look at it
but just like with micrograd i'm going
to build it out step by step and i'm
going to spell everything out so we're
going to build it out slowly and
together
now what is make more
make more as the name suggests
makes more of things that you give it
so here's an example
names.txt is an example dataset to make
more
and when you look at names.txt you'll
find that it's a very large data set of
names
so
here's lots of different types of names
in fact i believe there are 32 000 names
that i've sort of found randomly on the
government website
and if you train make more on this data
set it will learn to make more of things
like this
and in particular in this case that will
mean more things that sound name-like
but are actually unique names
and maybe if you have a baby and you're
trying to assign name maybe you're
looking for a cool new sounding unique
name make more might help you
so here are some example generations
from the neural network
once we train it on our data set
so here's some example
unique names that it will generate
dontel
irot
zhendi
and so on and so all these are sound
name like but they're not of course
names
so under the hood make more is a
character level language model so what
that means is that it is treating every
single line here as an example and
within each example it's treating them
all as sequences of individual
characters so r e e s e is this example
and that's the sequence of characters
and that's the level on which we are
building out make more and what it means
to be a character level language model
then is that it's just uh sort of
modeling those sequences of characters
and it knows how to predict the next
character in the sequence
now we're actually going to implement a
large number of character level language
models in terms of the neural networks
that are involved in predicting the next
character in a sequence so very simple
bi-gram and back of work models
multilingual perceptrons recurrent
neural networks all the way to modern
transformers in fact the transformer
that we will build will be basically the
equivalent transformer to gpt2 if you
have heard of gpt uh so that's kind of a
big deal it's a modern network and by
the end of the series you will actually
understand how that works um on the
level of characters now to give you a
sense of the extensions here uh after
characters we will probably spend some
time on the word level so that we can
generate documents of words not just
little you know segments of characters
but we can generate entire large much
larger documents
and then we're probably going to go into
images and image text
networks such as dolly stable diffusion
and so on but for now we have to start
here character level language modeling
let's go
so like before we are starting with a
completely blank jupiter notebook page
the first thing is i would like to
basically load up the dataset names.txt
so we're going to open up names.txt for
reading
and we're going to read in everything
into a massive string
and then because it's a massive string
we'd only like the individual words and
put them in the list
so let's call split lines
on that string
to get all of our words as a python list
of strings
so basically we can look at for example
the first 10 words
and we have that it's a list of emma
olivia eva and so on
and if we look at
the top of the page here that is indeed
what we see
um
so that's good
this list actually makes me feel that
this is probably sorted by frequency
but okay so
these are the words now we'd like to
actually like learn a little bit more
about this data set let's look at the
total number of words we expect this to
be roughly 32 000
and then what is the for example
shortest word
so min of
length of each word for w inwards
so the shortest word will be length
two
and max of one w for w in words so the
longest word will be
15 characters
so let's now think through our very
first language model
as i mentioned a character level
language model is predicting the next
character in a sequence given already
some concrete sequence of characters
before it
now we have to realize here is that
every single word here like isabella is
actually quite a few examples packed in
to that single word
because what is an existence of a word
like isabella in the data set telling us
really it's saying that
the character i is a very likely
character to come first in the sequence
of a name
the character s is likely to come
after i
the character a is likely to come after
is
the character b is very likely to come
after isa and so on all the way to a
following isabel
and then there's one more example
actually packed in here
and that is that
after there's isabella
the word is very likely to end
so that's one more sort of explicit
piece of information that we have here
that we have to be careful with
and so there's a lot backed into a
single individual word in terms of the
statistical structure of what's likely
to follow in these character sequences
and then of course we don't have just an
individual word we actually have 32 000
of these and so there's a lot of
structure here to model
now in the beginning what i'd like to
start with is i'd like to start with
building a bi-gram language model
now in the bigram language model we're
always working with just
two characters at a time
so we're only looking at one character
that we are given and we're trying to
predict the next character in the
sequence
so um what characters are likely to
follow are what characters are likely to
follow a and so on and we're just
modeling that kind of a little local
structure
and we're forgetting the fact that we
may have a lot more information we're
always just looking at the previous
character to predict the next one so
it's a very simple and weak language
model but i think it's a great place to
start
so now let's begin by looking at these
bi-grams in our data set and what they
look like and these bi-grams again are
just two characters in a row
so for w in words
each w here is an individual word a
string
we want to iterate uh for
we're going to iterate this word
with consecutive characters so two
characters at a time sliding it through
the word now a interesting nice way cute
way to do this in python by the way is
doing something like this for character
one character two in zip off
w and w at one
one column
print
character one character two
and let's not do all the words let's
just do the first three words and i'm
going to show you in a second how this
works
but for now basically as an example
let's just do the very first word alone
emma
you see how we have a emma and this will
just print e m m m a
and the reason this works is because w
is the string emma w at one column is
the string mma
and zip
takes two iterators and it pairs them up
and then creates an iterator over the
tuples of their consecutive entries
and if any one of these lists is shorter
than the other then it will just
halt and return
so basically that's why we return em mmm
ma
but then because this iterator second
one here runs out of elements zip just
ends and that's why we only get these
tuples so pretty cute
so these are the consecutive elements in
the first word now we have to be careful
because we actually have more
information here than just these three
examples as i mentioned we know that e
is the is very likely to come first and
we know that a in this case is coming
last
so one way to do this is basically we're
going to create
a special array here all
characters
and um we're going to hallucinate a
special start token here
i'm going to
call it like special start
so this is a list of one element
plus
w
and then plus a special end character
and the reason i'm wrapping the list of
w here is because w is a string emma
list of w will just have the individual
characters in the list
and then
doing this again now but not iterating
over w's but over the characters
will give us something like this
so e is likely so this is a bigram of
the start character and e and this is a
bigram of the
a and the special end character
and now we can look at for example what
this looks like for
olivia or eva
and indeed we can actually
potentially do this for the entire data
set but we won't print that that's going
to be too much
but these are the individual character
diagrams and we can print them
now in order to learn the statistics
about which characters are likely to
follow other characters the simplest way
in the bigram language models is to
simply do it by counting
so we're basically just going to count
how often any one of these combinations
occurs in the training set
in these words
so we're going to need some kind of a
dictionary that's going to maintain some
counts for every one of these diagrams
so let's use a dictionary b
and this will map these bi-grams so
bi-gram is a tuple of character one
character two
and then b at bi-gram
will be b dot get of bi-gram
which is basically the same as b at
bigram
but in the case that bigram is not in
the dictionary b we would like to by
default return to zero
plus one
so this will basically add up all the
bigrams and count how often they occur
let's get rid of printing
or rather
let's keep the printing and let's just
inspect what b is in this case
and we see that many bi-grams occur just
a single time this one allegedly
occurred three times
so a was an ending character three times
and that's true for all of these words
all of emma olivia and eva and with a
so that's why this occurred three times
now let's do it for all the words
oops i should not have printed
i'm going to erase that
let's kill this
let's just run
and now b will have the statistics of
the entire data set
so these are the counts across all the
words of the individual pie grams
and we could for example look at some of
the most common ones and least common
ones
this kind of grows in python but the way
to do this the simplest way i like is we
just use b dot items
b dot items returns
the tuples of
key value in this case the keys are
the character diagrams and the values
are the counts
and so then what we want to do is we
want to do
sorted of this
but by default sort is on the first
on the first item of a tuple but we want
to sort by the values which are the
second element of a tuple that is the
key value
so we want to use the key
equals lambda
that takes the key value
and returns
the key value at the one not at zero but
at one which is the count so we want to
sort by the count
of these elements
and actually we wanted to go backwards
so here we have is
the bi-gram q and r occurs only a single
time
dz occurred only a single time
and when we sort this the other way
around
we're going to see the most likely
bigrams so we see that n was
very often an ending character
many many times and apparently n almost
always follows an a
and that's a very likely combination as
well
so
this is kind of the individual counts
that we achieve over the entire data set
now it's actually going to be
significantly more convenient for us to
keep this information in a
two-dimensional array instead of a
python dictionary
so
we're going to store this information
in a 2d array
and
the rows are going to be the first
character of the bigram and the columns
are going to be the second character and
each entry in this two-dimensional array
will tell us how often that first
character files the second character in
the data set
so in particular the array
representation that we're going to use
or the library is that of pytorch
and pytorch is a deep
learning neural network framework but
part of it is also this torch.tensor
which allows us to create
multi-dimensional arrays and manipulate
them very efficiently
so
let's import pytorch which you can do by
import torch
and then we can create
arrays
so let's create a array of zeros
and we give it a
size of this array let's create a three
by five array as an example
and
this is a three by five array of zeros
and by default you'll notice a.d type
which is short for data type is float32
so these are single precision floating
point numbers
because we are going to represent counts
let's actually use d type as torch dot
and 32
so these are
32-bit integers
so now you see that we have integer data
inside this tensor
now tensors allow us to really
manipulate all the individual entries
and do it very efficiently
so for example if we want to change this
bit
we have to index into the tensor and in
particular here this is the first row
and the
because it's zero indexed so this is row
index one and column index zero one two
three
so a at one comma three we can set that
to one
and then a we'll have a 1 over there
we can of course also do things like
this so now a will be 2 over there
or 3.
and also we can for example say a 0 0 is
and then a will have a 5 over here
so that's how we can index into the
arrays now of course the array that we
are interested in is much much bigger so
for our purposes we have 26 letters of
the alphabet
and then we have two special characters
s and e
so uh we want 26 plus 2 or 28 by 28
array
and let's call it the capital n because
it's going to represent sort of the
counts
let me erase this stuff
so that's the array that starts at zeros
28 by 28
and now let's copy paste this
here
but instead of having a dictionary b
which we're going to erase we now have
an n
now the problem here is that we have
these characters which are strings but
we have to now
um basically index into a
um array and we have to index using
integers so we need some kind of a
lookup table from characters to integers
so let's construct such a character
array
and the way we're going to do this is
we're going to take all the words which
is a list of strings
we're going to concatenate all of it
into a massive string so this is just
simply the entire data set as a single
string
we're going to pass this to the set
constructor which takes this massive
string
and throws out duplicates because sets
do not allow duplicates
so set of this will just be the set of
all the lowercase characters
and there should be a total of 26 of
them
and now we actually don't want a set we
want a list
but we don't want a list sorted in some
weird arbitrary way we want it to be
sorted
from a to z
so sorted list
so those are our characters
now what we want is this lookup table as
i mentioned so let's create a special
s2i i will call it
um s is string or character and this
will be an s2i mapping
for
is in enumerate of these characters
so enumerate basically gives us this
iterator over the integer index and the
actual element of the list and then we
are mapping the character to the integer
so s2i
is a mapping from a to 0 b to 1 etc all
the way from z to 25
and that's going to be useful here but
we actually also have to specifically
set that s will be 26
and s to i at e will be 27 right because
z was 25.
so those are the lookups and now we can
come here and we can map
both character 1 and character 2 to
their integers
so this will be s2i at character 1
and ix2 will be s2i of character 2.
and now we should be able to
do this line but using our array so n at
x1 ix2 this is the two-dimensional array
indexing i've shown you before
and honestly just plus equals one
because everything starts at
zero
so this should
work
and give us a large 28 by 28 array
of all these counts so
if we print n
this is the array but of course it looks
ugly so let's erase this ugly mess and
let's try to visualize it a bit more
nicer
so for that we're going to use a library
called matplotlib
so matplotlib allows us to create
figures so we can do things like plt
item show of the counter array
so this is the 28x28 array
and this is structure but even this i
would say is still pretty ugly
so we're going to try to create a much
nicer visualization of it and i wrote a
bunch of code for that
the first thing we're going to need is
we're going to need to invert
this array here this dictionary so s2i
is mapping from s to i
and in i2s we're going to reverse this
dictionary so iterator of all the items
and just reverse that array
so i2s
maps inversely from 0 to a 1 to b etc
so we'll need that
and then here's the code that i came up
with to try to make this a little bit
nicer
we create a figure
we plot
n
and then we do and then we visualize a
bunch of things later let me just run it
so you get a sense of what this is
okay
so you see here that we have
the array spaced out
and every one of these is basically like
b follows g zero times
b follows h 41 times
um so a follows j 175 times
and so what you can see that i'm doing
here is first i show that entire array
and then i iterate over all the
individual little cells here
and i create a character string here
which is the inverse mapping i2s of the
integer i and the integer j so those are
the bi-grams in a character
representation
and then i plot just the diagram text
and then i plot the number of times that
this bigram occurs
now the reason that there's a dot item
here is because when you index into
these arrays these are torch tensors
you see that we still get a tensor back
so the type of this thing you'd think it
would be just an integer 149 but it's
actually a torch.tensor
and so
if you do dot item then it will pop out
that in individual integer
so it will just be 149.
so that's what's happening there and
these are just some options to make it
look nice
so what is the structure of this array
we have all these counts and we see that
some of them occur often and some of
them do not occur often
now if you scrutinize this carefully you
will notice that we're not actually
being very clever
that's because when you come over here
you'll notice that for example we have
an entire row of completely zeros and
that's because the end character
is never possibly going to be the first
character of a bi-gram because we're
always placing these end tokens all at
the end of the diagram
similarly we have entire columns zeros
here because the s
character will never possibly be the
second element of a bigram because we
always start with s and we end with e
and we only have the words in between
so we have an entire column of zeros an
entire row of zeros and in this little
two by two matrix here as well the only
one that can possibly happen is if s
directly follows e
that can be non-zero if we have a word
that has no letters so in that case
there's no letters in the word it's an
empty word and we just have s follows e
but the other ones are just not possible
and so we're basically wasting space and
not only that but the s and the e are
getting very crowded here
i was using these brackets because
there's convention and natural language
processing to use these kinds of
brackets to denote special tokens
but we're going to use something else
so let's fix all this and make it
prettier
we're not actually going to have two
special tokens we're only going to have
one special token
so
we're going to have n by n
array of 27 by 27 instead
instead of having two
we will just have one and i will call it
a dot
okay
let me swing this over here
now one more thing that i would like to
do is i would actually like to make this
special character half position zero
and i would like to offset all the other
letters off i find that a little bit
more
pleasing
so
we need a plus one here so that the
first character which is a will start at
one
so s2i
will now be a starts at one and dot is 0
and
i2s of course we're not changing this
because i2s just creates a reverse
mapping and this will work fine so 1 is
a 2 is b
0 is dot
so we've reversed that here
we have
a dot and a dot
this should work fine
make sure i start at zeros
count
and then here we don't go up to 28 we go
up to 27
and this should just work
okay
so we see that dot never happened it's
at zero because we don't have empty
words
then this row here now is just uh very
simply the um
counts for all the first letters so
uh j starts a word h starts a word i
starts a word etc and then these are all
the ending
characters
and in between we have the structure of
what characters follow each other
so this is the counts array of our
entire
data set so this array actually has all
the information necessary for us to
actually sample from this bigram
uh character level language model
and um roughly speaking what we're going
to do is we're just going to start
following these probabilities and these
counts and we're going to start sampling
from the from the model
so in the beginning of course
we start with the dot the start token
dot
so to sample the first character of a
name we're looking at this row here
so we see that we have the counts and
those concepts terminally are telling us
how often any one of these characters is
to start a word
so if we take this n
and we grab the first row
we can do that by using just indexing as
zero
and then using this notation column for
the rest of that row
so n zero colon
is indexing into the zeroth
row and then it's grabbing all the
columns
and so this will give us a
one-dimensional array
of the first row so zero four four ten
you know zero four four ten one three oh
six one five four two etc it's just the
first row the shape of this
is 27 it's just the row of 27
and the other way that you can do this
also is you just you don't need to
actually give this
you just grab the zeroth row like this
this is equivalent
now these are the counts
and now what we'd like to do is we'd
like to basically um sample from this
since these are the raw counts we
actually have to convert this to
probabilities
so we create a probability vector
so we'll take n of zero
and we'll actually convert this to float
first
okay so these integers are converted to
float
floating point numbers and the reason
we're creating floats is because we're
about to normalize these counts
so to create a probability distribution
here we want to divide
we basically want to do p p p divide p
that sum
and now we get a vector of smaller
numbers and these are now probabilities
so of course because we divided by the
sum the sum of p now is 1.
so this is a nice proper probability
distribution it sums to 1 and this is
giving us the probability for any single
character to be the first
character of a word
so now we can try to sample from this
distribution to sample from these
distributions we're going to use
storch.multinomial which i've pulled up
here
so torch.multinomial returns uh
samples from the multinomial probability
distribution which is a complicated way
of saying you give me probabilities and
i will give you integers which are
sampled
according to the property distribution
so this is the signature of the method
and to make everything deterministic
we're going to use a generator object in
pytorch
so this makes everything deterministic
so when you run this on your computer
you're going to the exact get the exact
same results that i'm getting here on my
computer
so let me show you how this works
here's the deterministic way of creating
a torch generator object
seeding it with some number that we can
agree on
so that seeds a generator gets gives us
an object g
and then we can pass that g
to a function
that creates um
here random numbers twerk.rand creates
random numbers three of them
and it's using this generator object to
as a source of randomness
so
without normalizing it
i can just print
this is sort of like numbers between 0
and 1 that are random according to this
thing and whenever i run it again
i'm always going to get the same result
because i keep using the same generator
object which i'm seeing here
and then if i divide
to normalize i'm going to get a nice
probability distribution of just three
elements
and then we can use torsion multinomial
to draw samples from it so this is what
that looks like
tertiary multinomial we'll take the
torch tensor
of probability distributions
then we can ask for a number of samples
let's say 20.
replacement equals true means that when
we draw an element
we will uh we can draw it and then we
can put it back into the list of
eligible indices to draw again
and we have to specify replacement as
true because by default uh for some
reason it's false
and i think
you know it's just something to be
careful with
and the generator is passed in here so
we're going to always get deterministic
results the same results so if i run
these two
we're going to get a bunch of samples
from this distribution
now you'll notice here that the
probability for the
first element in this tensor is 60
so in these 20 samples we'd expect 60 of
them to be zero
we'd expect thirty percent of them to be
one
and because the the element index two
has only ten percent probability very
few of these samples should be two and
indeed we only have a small number of
twos
and we can sample as many as we'd like
and the more we sample the more
these numbers should um roughly have the
distribution here
so we should have lots of zeros
half as many um
ones and we should have um three times
as few
oh sorry s few ones and three times as
few uh
twos
so you see that we have very few twos we
have some ones and most of them are zero
so that's what torsion multinomial is
doing
for us here
we are interested in this row we've
created this
p here
and now we can sample from it
so if we use the same
seed
and then we sample from this
distribution let's just get one sample
then we see that the sample is say 13.
so this will be the index
and let's you see how it's a tensor that
wraps 13 we again have to use that item
to pop out that integer
and now index would be just the number
13.
and of course the um we can do
we can map the i2s of ix to figure out
exactly which character
we're sampling here we're sampling m
so we're saying that the first character
is
in our generation
and just looking at the road here
m was drawn and you we can see that m
actually starts a large number of words
uh m
started 2 500 words out of 32 000 words
so almost
a bit less than 10 percent of the words
start with them so this was actually a
fairly likely character to draw
um
so that would be the first character of
our work and now we can continue to
sample more characters because now we
know that m started
m is already sampled
so now to draw the next character we
will come back here and we will look for
the row
that starts with m
so you see m
and we have a row here
so we see that m dot is
516 m a is this many and b is this many
etc so these are the counts for the next
row and that's the next character that
we are going to now generate
so i think we are ready to actually just
write out the loop because i think
you're starting to get a sense of how
this is going to go
the um
we always begin at
index 0 because that's the start token
and then while true
we're going to grab the row
corresponding to index
that we're currently on so that's p
so that's n array at ix
converted to float is rp
then we normalize
this p to sum to one
i accidentally ran the infinite loop we
normalize p to something one
then we need this generator object
now we're going to initialize up here
and we're going to draw a single sample
from this distribution
and then this is going to tell us what
index is going to be next
if the index sampled is
then that's now the end token
so we will break
otherwise we are going to print
s2i of ix
i2s
and uh that's pretty much it we're just
uh this should work okay more
so that's that's the name that we've
sampled we started with m the next step
was o then r and then dot
and this dot we it here as well
so
let's now do this a few times
so let's actually create an
out list here
and instead of printing we're going to
append
so out that append this character
and then here let's just print it at the
end so let's just join up all the outs
and we're just going to print more okay
now we're always getting the same result
because of the generator
so if we want to do this a few times we
can go for i in range
10 we can sample 10 names
and we can just do that 10 times
and these are the names that we're
getting out
let's do 20.
i'll be honest with you this doesn't
look right
so i started a few minutes to convince
myself that it actually is right
the reason these samples are so terrible
is that bigram language model
is actually look just like really
terrible
we can generate a few more here
and you can see that they're kind of
like their name like a little bit like
yanu o'reilly etc but they're just like
totally messed up um
and i mean the reason that this is so
bad like we're generating h as a name
but you have to think through
it from the model's eyes it doesn't know
that this h is the very first h all it
knows is that h was previously and now
how likely is h the last character well
it's somewhat
likely and so it just makes it last
character it doesn't know that there
were other things before it or there
were not other things before it and so
that's why it's generating all these
like
nonsense names
another way to do this is
to convince yourself that this is
actually doing something reasonable even
though it's so terrible is
these little piece here are 27 right
like 27.
so how about if we did something like
this
instead of p having any structure
whatsoever
how about if p was just
torch dot once
of 27
by default this is a float 32 so this is
fine divide 27
so what i'm doing here is this is the
uniform distribution which will make
everything equally likely
and we can sample from that so let's see
if that does any better
okay so it's
this is what you have from a model that
is completely untrained where everything
is equally likely so it's obviously
garbage and then if we have a trained
model which is trained on just bi-grams
this is what we get so you can see that
it is more name-like it is actually
working it's just um
my gram is so terrible and we have to do
better now next i would like to fix an
inefficiency that we have going on here
because what we're doing here is we're
always fetching a row of n from the
counts matrix up ahead
and then we're always doing the same
things we're converting to float and
we're dividing and we're doing this
every single iteration of this loop and
we just keep renormalizing these rows
over and over again and it's extremely
inefficient and wasteful so what i'd
like to do is i'd like to actually
prepare a matrix capital p that will
just have the probabilities in it so in
other words it's going to be the same as
the capital n matrix here of counts but
every single row will have the row of
probabilities uh that is normalized to 1
indicating the probability distribution
for the next character given the
character before it
um as defined by which row we're in
so basically what we'd like to do is
we'd like to just do it up front here
and then we would like to just use that
row here so here we would like to just
do p equals p of ix instead
okay
the other reason i want to do this is
not just for efficiency but also i would
like us to practice
these n-dimensional tensors and i'd like
us to practice their manipulation and
especially something that's called
broadcasting that we'll go into in a
second
we're actually going to have to become
very good at these tensor manipulations
because if we're going to build out all
the way to transformers we're going to
be doing some pretty complicated um
array operations for efficiency and we
need to really understand that and be
very good at it
so intuitively what we want to do is we
first want to grab the floating point
copy of n
and i'm mimicking the line here
basically
and then we want to divide all the rows
so that they sum to 1.
so we'd like to do something like this p
divide p dot sum
but
now we have to be careful
because p dot sum actually
produces a sum
sorry equals and that float copy
p dot sum produces a um
sums up all of the counts of this entire
matrix n and gives us a single number of
just the summation of everything so
that's not the way we want to define
divide we want to simultaneously and in
parallel divide all the rows
by their respective sums
so what we have to do now is we have to
go into documentation for torch.sum
and we can scroll down here to a
definition that is relevant to us which
is where we don't only provide an input
array that we want to sum but we also
provide the dimension along which we
want to sum
and in particular we want to sum up
over rows
right
now one more argument that i want you to
pay attention to here is the keep them
is false
if keep them is true then the output
tensor is of the same size as input
except of course the dimension along
which is summed which will become just
one
but if you pass in keep them as false
then this dimension is squeezed out and
so torch.sum not only does the sum and
collapses dimension to be of size one
but in addition it does what's called a
squeeze where it squeezes out it
squeezes out that dimension
so
basically what we want here is we
instead want to do p dot sum of some
axis
and in particular notice that p dot
shape is 27 by 27
so when we sum up across axis zero then
we would be taking the zeroth dimension
and we would be summing across it
so when keep them as true
then this thing will not only give us
the counts across um
along the columns
but notice that basically the shape of
this is 1 by 27 we just get a row vector
and the reason we get a row vector here
again is because we passed in zero
dimension so this zero dimension becomes
one and we've done a sum
and we get a row and so basically we've
done the sum
this way
vertically and arrived at just a single
1 by 27
vector of counts
what happens when you take out keep them
is that we just get 27. so it squeezes
out that dimension and we just get
a one-dimensional vector of size 27.
now we don't actually want
one by 27 row vector because that gives
us the counts or the sums across
the columns
we actually want to sum the other way
along dimension one and you'll see that
the shape of this is 27 by one so it's a
column vector it's a 27 by one
vector of counts
okay
and that's because what's happened here
is that we're going horizontally and
this 27 by 27 matrix becomes a 27 by 1
array
now you'll notice by the way that um the
actual numbers
of these counts are identical
and that's because this special array of
counts here comes from bi-gram
statistics and actually it just so
happens by chance
or because of the way this array is
constructed that the sums along the
columns or along the rows horizontally
or vertically is identical
but actually what we want to do in this
case is we want to sum across the
rows
horizontally so what we want here is p
that sum of one with keep in true
27 by one column vector
and now what we want to do is we want to
divide by that
now we have to be careful here again is
it possible to take
what's a um p dot shape you see here 27
by 27 is it possible to take a 27 by 27
array and divide it by what is a 27 by 1
array
is that an operation that you can do
and whether or not you can perform this
operation is determined by what's called
broadcasting rules so if you just search
broadcasting semantics in torch
you'll notice that there's a special
definition for
what's called broadcasting that uh for
whether or not um these two uh arrays
can be combined in a binary operation
like division
so the first condition is each tensor
has at least one dimension which is the
case for us
and then when iterating over the
dimension sizes starting at the trailing
dimension
the dimension sizes must either be equal
one of them is one or one of them does
not exist
okay
so let's do that we need to align the
two arrays and their shapes which is
very easy because both of these shapes
have two elements so they're aligned
then we iterate over from the from the
right and going to the left
each dimension must be either equal one
of them is a one or one of them does not
exist so in this case they're not equal
but one of them is a one so this is fine
and then this dimension they're both
equal
so uh this is fine
so all the dimensions are fine and
therefore the this operation is
broadcastable so that means that this
operation is allowed
and what is it that these arrays do when
you divide 27 by 27 by 27 by one
what it does is that it takes this
dimension one and it stretches it out it
copies it to match
27 here in this case
so in our case it takes this column
vector which is 27 by 1
and it copies it 27 times
to make
these both be 27 by 27 internally you
can think of it that way and so it
copies those counts
and then it does an element-wise
division
which is what we want because these
counts we want to divide by them on
every single one of these columns in
this matrix
so this actually we expect will
normalize
every single row
and we can check that this is true by
taking the first row for example and
taking its sum we expect this to be
1. because it's not normalized
and then we expect this now because if
we actually correctly normalize all the
rows we expect to get the exact same
result here so let's run this
it's the exact same result
this is correct so now i would like to
scare you a little bit
uh you actually have to like i basically
encourage you very strongly to read
through broadcasting semantics
and i encourage you to treat this with
respect and it's not something to play
fast and loose with it's something to
really respect really understand and
look up maybe some tutorials for
broadcasting and practice it and be
careful with it because you can very
quickly run into books let me show you
what i mean
you see how here we have p dot sum of
one keep them as true
the shape of this is 27 by one let me
take out this line just so we have the n
and then we can see the counts
we can see that this is a all the counts
across all the
rows
and it's a 27 by one column vector right
now suppose that i tried to do the
following
but i erase keep them just true here
what does that do if keep them is not
true it's false then remember according
to documentation it gets rid of this
dimension one it squeezes it out so
basically we just get all the same
counts the same result except the shape
of it is not 27 by 1 it is just 27 the
one disappears
but all the counts are the same
so you'd think that this divide that
would uh would work
first of all can we even uh write this
and will it is it even is it even
expected to run is it broadcastable
let's determine if this result is
broadcastable
p.summit one is shape
is 27.
this is 27 by 27. so 27 by 27
broadcasting into 27. so now
rules of broadcasting number one align
all the dimensions on the right done now
iteration over all the dimensions
starting from the right going to the
left
all the dimensions must either be equal
one of them must be one or one that does
not exist so here they are all equal
here the dimension does not exist
so internally what broadcasting will do
is it will create a one here
and then
we see that one of them is a one and
this will get copied and this will run
this will broadcast
okay so you'd expect this
to work
because we we are
this broadcast and this we can divide
this
now if i run this you'd expect it to
work but
it doesn't
uh you actually get garbage you get a
wrong dissolve because this is actually
a bug
this keep them equals true
makes it work
this is a bug
in both cases we are doing
the correct counts we are summing up
across the rows
but keep them is saving us and making it
work so in this case
i'd like to encourage you to potentially
like pause this video at this point and
try to think about why this is buggy and
why the keep dim was necessary here
okay
so the reason to do
for this is i'm trying to hint it here
when i was sort of giving you a bit of a
hint on how this works
this
27 vector
internally inside the broadcasting this
becomes a 1 by 27
and 1 by 27 is a row vector right
and now we are dividing 27 by 27 by 1 by
and torch will replicate this dimension
so basically
uh it will take
it will take this
row vector and it will copy it
vertically now
27 times so the 27 by 27 lies exactly
and element wise divides
and so basically what's happening here
is
we're actually normalizing the columns
instead of normalizing the rows
so you can check that what's happening
here is that p at zero which is the
first row of p dot sum
is not one it's seven
it is the first column as an example
that sums to one
so
to summarize where does the issue come
from the issue comes from the silent
adding of a dimension here because in
broadcasting rules you align on the
right and go from right to left and if
dimension doesn't exist you create it
so that's where the problem happens we
still did the counts correctly we did
the counts across the rows and we got
the the counts on the right here as a
column vector but because the keep
things was true this this uh this
dimension was discarded and now we just
have a vector of 27. and because of
broadcasting the way it works this
vector of 27 suddenly becomes a row
vector
and then this row vector gets replicated
vertically and that every single point
we are dividing by the by the count
in the opposite direction
so uh
so this thing just uh doesn't work this
needs to be keep things equal true in
this case
so then
then we have that p at zero is
normalized
and conversely the first column you'd
expect to potentially not be normalized
and this is what makes it work
so pretty subtle and uh hopefully this
helps to scare you that you should have
a respect for broadcasting be careful
check your work uh and uh understand how
it works under the hood and make sure
that it's broadcasting in the direction
that you like otherwise you're going to
introduce very subtle bugs very hard to
find bugs and uh just be careful one
more note on efficiency we don't want to
be doing this here because this creates
a completely new tensor that we store
into p
we prefer to use in place operations if
possible
so this would be an in-place operation
it has the potential to be faster it
doesn't create new memory
under the hood and then let's erase this
we don't need it
and let's
also
um just do fewer just so i'm not wasting
space
okay so we're actually in a pretty good
spot now
we trained a bigram language model and
we trained it really just by counting uh
how frequently any pairing occurs and
then normalizing so that we get a nice
property distribution
so really these elements of this array p
are really the parameters of our biogram
language model giving us and summarizing
the statistics of these bigrams
so we train the model and then we know
how to sample from a model we just
iteratively uh sample the next character
and feed it in each time and get a next
character
now what i'd like to do is i'd like to
somehow evaluate the quality of this
model we'd like to somehow summarize the
quality of this model into a single
number how good is it at predicting
the training set
and as an example so in the training set
we can evaluate now the training loss
and this training loss is telling us
about
sort of the quality of this model in a
single number just like we saw in
micrograd
so let's try to think through the
quality of the model and how we would
evaluate it
basically what we're going to do is
we're going to copy paste this code
that we previously used for counting
okay
and let me just print these diagrams
first we're gonna use f strings
and i'm gonna print character one
followed by character two these are the
diagrams and then i don't wanna do it
for all the words just do the first
three words so here we have emma olivia
and ava bigrams
now what we'd like to do is we'd like to
basically look at the probability that
the model assigns to every one of these
diagrams
so in other words we can look at the
probability which is
summarized in the matrix b
of i x 1 x 2
and then we can print it here
as probability
and because these properties are way too
large let me present
or call in 0.4 f
to like truncate it a bit
so what do we have here right we're
looking at the probabilities that the
model assigns to every one of these
bigrams in the dataset
and so we can see some of them are four
percent three percent etc
just to have a measuring stick in our
mind by the way um we have 27 possible
characters or tokens and if everything
was equally likely then you'd expect all
these probabilities
to be
four percent roughly
so anything above four percent means
that we've learned something useful from
these bigram statistics and you see that
roughly some of these are four percent
but some of them are as high as 40
percent
35 percent and so on so you see that the
model actually assigned a pretty high
probability to whatever's in the
training set and so that's a good thing
um basically if you have a very good
model you'd expect that these
probabilities should be near one because
that means that your model is correctly
predicting what's going to come next
especially on the training set where you
where you trained your model
so
now we'd like to think about how can we
summarize these probabilities into a
single number that measures the quality
of this model
now when you look at the literature into
maximum likelihood estimation and
statistical modeling and so on
you'll see that what's typically used
here is something called the likelihood
and the likelihood is the product of all
of these probabilities
and so the product of all these
probabilities is the likelihood and it's
really telling us about the probability
of the entire data set assigned uh
assigned by the model that we've trained
and that is a measure of quality
so the product of these
should be as high as possible
when you are training the model and when
you have a good model your pro your
product of these probabilities should be
very high
um
now because the product of these
probabilities is an unwieldy thing to
work with you can see that all of them
are between zero and one so your product
of these probabilities will be a very
tiny number
um
so
for convenience what people work with
usually is not the likelihood but they
work with what's called the log
likelihood
so
the product of these is the likelihood
to get the log likelihood we just have
to take the log of the probability
and so the log of the probability here i
have the log of x from zero to one
the log is a you see here monotonic
transformation of the probability
where if you pass in one
you get zero
so probability one gets your log
probability of zero
and then as you go lower and lower
probability the log will grow more and
more negative until all the way to
negative infinity at zero
so here we have a log prob which is
really just a torch.log of probability
let's print it out to get a sense of
what that looks like
log prob
also 0.4 f
okay
so as you can see when we plug in
numbers that are very close some of our
higher numbers we get closer and closer
to zero
and then if we plug in very bad
probabilities we get more and more
negative number that's bad
so
and the reason we work with this is for
a large extent convenience right
because we have mathematically that if
you have some product a times b times c
of all these probabilities right
the likelihood is the product of all
these probabilities
then the log
of these
is just log of a plus
log of b
plus log of c if you remember your logs
from your
high school or undergrad and so on
so we have that basically
the likelihood of the product
probabilities the log likelihood is just
the sum of the logs of the individual
probabilities
so
log likelihood
starts at zero
and then log likelihood here we can just
accumulate simply
and in the end we can print this
print the log likelihood
f strings
maybe you're familiar with this
so log likelihood is negative 38.
okay
now
we actually want um
so how high can log likelihood get it
can go to zero so when all the
probabilities are one log likelihood
will be zero and then when all the
probabilities are lower this will grow
more and more negative
now we don't actually like this because
what we'd like is a loss function and a
loss function has the semantics that low
is good
because we're trying to minimize the
loss so we actually need to invert this
and that's what gives us something
called the negative log likelihood
negative log likelihood is just negative
of the log likelihood
these are f strings by the way if you'd
like to look this up
negative log likelihood equals
so negative log likelihood now is just
negative of it and so the negative log
block load is a very nice loss function
because um
the lowest it can get is zero
and the higher it is the worse off the
predictions are that you're making
and then one more modification to this
that sometimes people do is that for
convenience uh they actually like to
normalize by they like to make it an
average instead of a sum
and so uh here
let's just keep some counts as well
so n plus equals one
starts at zero
and then here
um we can have sort of like a normalized
log likelihood
um
if we just normalize it by the count
then we will sort of get the average
log likelihood so this would be
usually our loss function here is what
this we would this is what we would use
uh so our loss function for the training
set assigned by the model is 2.4 that's
the quality of this model
and the lower it is the better off we
are and the higher it is the worse off
we are
and
the job of our you know training is to
find the parameters that minimize the
negative log likelihood loss
and that would be like a high quality
model okay so to summarize i actually
wrote it out here
so our goal is to maximize likelihood
which is the
product of all the probabilities
assigned by the model
and we want to maximize this likelihood
with respect to the model parameters and
in our case the model parameters here
are defined in the table these numbers
the probabilities
are
the model parameters sort of in our
program language models so far but you
have to keep in mind that here we are
storing everything in a table format the
probabilities but what's coming up as a
brief preview is that these numbers will
not be kept explicitly but these numbers
will be calculated by a neural network
so that's coming up
and we want to change and tune the
parameters of these neural networks we
want to change these parameters to
maximize the likelihood the product of
the probabilities
now maximizing the likelihood is
equivalent to maximizing the log
likelihood because log is a monotonic
function
here's the graph of log
and basically all it is doing is it's
just scaling your um you can look at it
as just a scaling of the loss function
and so the optimization problem here and
here are actually equivalent because
this is just scaling you can look at it
that way
and so these are two identical
optimization problems
um
maximizing the log-likelihood is
equivalent to minimizing the negative
log likelihood and then in practice
people actually minimize the average
negative log likelihood to get numbers
like 2.4
and then this summarizes the quality of
your model and we'd like to minimize it
and make it as small as possible
and the lowest it can get is zero
and the lower it is
the better off your model is because
it's signing it's assigning high
probabilities to your data now let's
estimate the probability over the entire
training set just to make sure that we
get something around 2.4 let's run this
over the entire oops
let's take out the print segment as well
okay 2.45 or the entire training set
now what i'd like to show you is that
you can actually evaluate the
probability for any word that you want
like for example
if we just test a single word andre and
bring back the print statement
then you see that andre is actually kind
of like an unlikely word like on average
we take
three
log probability to represent it and
roughly that's because ej apparently is
very uncommon as an example
now
think through this um
when i take andre and i append q and i
test the probability of it under q
we actually get
infinity
and that's because jq has a zero percent
probability according to our model so
the log likelihood
so the log of zero will be negative
infinity we get infinite loss
so this is kind of undesirable right
because we plugged in a string that
could be like a somewhat reasonable name
but basically what this is saying is
that this model is exactly zero percent
likely to uh to predict this
name
and our loss is infinity on this example
and really what the reason for that is
that j
is followed by q
uh zero times
uh where's q jq is zero and so jq is uh
zero percent likely
so it's actually kind of gross and
people don't like this too much to fix
this there's a very simple fix that
people like to do to sort of like smooth
out your model a little bit and it's
called model smoothing and roughly
what's happening is that we will eight
we will add some fake counts
so
imagine adding a count of one to
everything
so we add a count of one
like this
and then we recalculate the
probabilities
and that's model smoothing and you can
add as much as you like you can add five
and it will give you a smoother model
and the more you add here
the more
uniform model you're going to have and
the less you add
the more peaked model you are going to
have of course
so one is like a pretty decent count to
add
and that will ensure that there will be
no zeros in our probability matrix p
and so this will of course change the
generations a little bit in this case it
didn't but in principle it could
but what that's going to do now is that
nothing will be infinity unlikely
so now
our model will predict some other
probability and we see that jq now has a
very small probability so the model
still finds it very surprising that this
was a word or a bigram but we don't get
negative infinity so it's kind of like a
nice fix that people like to apply
sometimes and it's called model
smoothing okay so we've now trained a
respectable bi-gram character level
language model and we saw that we both
sort of trained the model by looking at
the counts of all the bigrams and
normalizing the rows to get probability
distributions
we saw that we can also then use those
parameters of this model to perform
sampling of new words
so we sample new names according to
those distributions and we also saw that
we can evaluate the quality of this
model and the quality of this model is
summarized in a single number which is
the negative log likelihood and the
lower this number is the better the
model is
because it is giving high probabilities
to the actual next characters in all the
bi-grams in our training set
so that's all well and good but we've
arrived at this model explicitly by
doing something that felt sensible we
were just performing counts and then we
were normalizing those counts
now what i would like to do is i would
like to take an alternative approach we
will end up in a very very similar
position but the approach will look very
different because i would like to cast
the problem of bi-gram character level
language modeling into the neural
network framework
in the neural network framework we're
going to approach things slightly
differently but again end up in a very
similar spot i'll go into that later now
our neural network is going to be a
still a background character level
language model so it receives a single
character as an input
then there's neural network with some
weights or some parameters w
and it's going to output the probability
distribution over the next character in
a sequence it's going to make guesses as
to what is likely to follow this
character that was input to the model
and then in addition to that we're going
to be able to evaluate any setting of
the parameters of the neural net because
we have the loss function
the negative log likelihood so we're
going to take a look at its probability
distributions and we're going to use the
labels
which are basically just the identity of
the next character in that diagram the
second character
so knowing what second character
actually comes next in the bigram allows
us to then look at what how high of
probability the model assigns to that
character
and then we of course want the
probability to be very high
and that is another way of saying that
the loss is low
so we're going to use gradient-based
optimization then to tune the parameters
of this network because we have the loss
function and we're going to minimize it
so we're going to tune the weights so
that the neural net is correctly
predicting the probabilities for the
next character
so let's get started the first thing i
want to do is i want to compile the
training set of this neural network
right so
create
the training set
of all the bigrams
okay
and
here
i'm going to copy paste this code
because this code iterates over all the
programs
so here we start with the words we
iterate over all the bygrams and
previously as you recall we did the
counts but now we're not going to do
counts we're just creating a training
set
now this training set will be made up of
two lists
we have the
inputs
and the targets
the the labels
and these bi-grams will denote x y those
are the characters right
and so we're given the first character
of the bi-gram and then we're trying to
predict the next one
both of these are going to be integers
so here we'll take x's that append is
just
x1 ystat append ix2
and then here
we actually don't want lists of integers
we will create tensors out of these so
axis is torch.tensor of axis and wise a
storage.tensor of ys
and then
we don't actually want to take all the
words just yet because i want everything
to be manageable
so let's just do the first word which is
emma
and then it's clear what these x's and
y's would be
here let me print
character 1 character 2 just so you see
what's going on here
so the bigrams of these characters is
dot e e m m m a a dot so this single
word as i mentioned has one two three
four five examples for our neural
network
there are five separate examples in emma
and those examples are summarized here
when the input to the neural network is
integer 0
the desired label is integer 5 which
corresponds to e when the input to the
neural network is 5 we want its weights
to be arranged so that 13 gets a very
high probability
when 13 is put in we want 13 to have a
when 13 is put in we also want 1 to have
a high probability
when one is input we want zero to have a
very high probability so there are five
separate input examples to a neural nut
in this data set
i wanted to add a tangent of a node of
caution to be careful with a lot of the
apis of some of these frameworks
you saw me silently use torch.tensor
with a lowercase t
and the output looked right
but you should be aware that there's
actually two ways of constructing a
tensor there's a torch.lowercase tensor
and there's also a torch.capital tensor
class which you can also construct
so you can actually call both you can
also do torch.capital tensor
and you get a nexus and wise as well
so that's not confusing at all
um
there are threads on what is the
difference between these two
and um
unfortunately the docs are just like not
clear on the difference and when you
look at the the docs of lower case
tensor construct tensor with no autograd
history by copying data
it's just like it doesn't
it doesn't make sense so the actual
difference as far as i can tell is
explained eventually in this random
thread that you can google
and really it comes down to
i believe
that um
what is this
torch.tensor in first d-type the data
type automatically while torch.tensor
just returns a float tensor
i would recommend stick to
torch.lowercase tensor
so um
indeed we see that when i
construct this with a capital t the data
type here of xs is float32
but towards that lowercase tensor
you see how it's now x dot d type is now
integer
so um
it's advised that you use lowercase t
and you can read more about it if you
like in some of these threads but
basically
um
i'm pointing out some of these things
because i want to caution you and i want
you to re get used to reading a lot of
documentation and reading through a lot
of
q and a's and threads like this
and
you know some of the stuff is
unfortunately not easy and not very well
documented and you have to be careful
out there what we want here is integers
because that's what makes uh sense
um
and so
lowercase tensor is what we are using
okay now we want to think through how
we're going to feed in these examples
into a neural network
now it's not quite as straightforward as
plugging it in because these examples
right now are integers so there's like a
0 5 or 13 it gives us the index of the
character and you can't just plug an
integer index into a neural net
these neural nets right are sort of made
up of these neurons
and
these neurons have weights and as you
saw in micrograd these weights act
multiplicatively on the inputs w x plus
b there's 10 h's and so on and so it
doesn't really make sense to make an
input neuron take on integer values that
you feed in and then multiply on with
weights
so instead
a common way of encoding integers is
what's called one hot encoding
in one hot encoding
we take an integer like 13 and we create
a vector that is all zeros except for
the 13th dimension which we turn to a
one and then that vector can feed into a
neural net
now conveniently
uh pi torch actually has something
called the one hot
function inside torching and functional
it takes a tensor made up of integers
um
long is a is a as an integer
and it also takes a number of classes um
which is how large you want your uh
tensor uh your vector to be
so here let's import
torch.n.functional sf this is a common
way of importing it
and then let's do f.1 hot
and we feed in the integers that we want
to encode so we can actually feed in the
entire array of x's
and we can tell it that num classes is
27.
so it doesn't have to try to guess it it
may have guessed that it's only 13 and
would give us an incorrect result
so this is the one hot let's call this x
inc for x encoded
and then we see that x encoded that
shape is 5 by 27
and uh we can also visualize it plt.i am
show of x inc
to make it a little bit more clear
because this is a little messy
so we see that we've encoded all the
five examples uh into vectors we have
five examples so we have five rows and
each row here is now an example into a
neural nut
and we see that the appropriate bit is
turned on as a one and everything else
is zero
so um
here for example the zeroth bit is
turned on the fifth bit is turned on
13th bits are turned on for both of
these examples and then the first bit
here is turned on
so that's how we can encode
integers into vectors and then these
vectors can feed in to neural nets one
more issue to be careful with here by
the way is
let's look at the data type of encoding
we always want to be careful with data
types
what would you expect x encoding's data
type to be
when we're plugging numbers into neural
nuts we don't want them to be integers
we want them to be floating point
numbers that can take on various values
but the d type here is actually 64-bit
integer
and the reason for that i suspect is
that one hot received a 64-bit integer
here and it returned the same data type
and when you look at the signature of
one hot it doesn't even take a d type a
desired data type of the output tensor
and so we can't in a lot of functions in
torch we'd be able to do something like
d type equal storage.float32
which is what we want but one heart does
not support that
so instead we're going to want to cast
this to float like this
so that these
everything is the same
everything looks the same but the d-type
is float32 and floats can feed into
neural nets so now let's construct our
first neuron
this neuron will look at these input
vectors
and as you remember from micrograd these
neurons basically perform a very simple
function w x plus b where w x is a dot
product
right
so we can achieve the same thing here
let's first define the weights of this
neuron basically what are the initial
weights at initialization for this
neuron
let's initialize them with torch.rendin
torch.rendin
is um
fills a tensor with random numbers
drawn from a normal distribution
and a normal distribution
has
a probability density function like this
and so most of the numbers drawn from
this distribution will be around 0
but some of them will be as high as
almost three and so on and very few
numbers will be above three in magnitude
so we need to take a size as an input
here
and i'm going to use size as to be 27 by
one
so
27 by one and then let's visualize w so
w is a column vector of 27 numbers
and
these weights are then multiplied by the
inputs
so now to perform this multiplication we
can take x encoding and we can multiply
it with w
this is a matrix multiplication operator
in pi torch
and the output of this operation is five
by one
the reason is five by five is the
following
we took x encoding which is five by
twenty seven and we multiplied it by
twenty seven by one
and
in matrix multiplication
you see that the output will become five
by one because these 27
will multiply and add
so basically what we're seeing here outs
out of this operation
is we are seeing the five
activations
of this neuron
on these five inputs
and we've evaluated all of them in
parallel we didn't feed in just a single
input to the single neuron we fed in
simultaneously all the five inputs into
the same neuron
and in parallel patrol has evaluated
the wx plus b but here is just the wx
there's no bias
it has value w times x for all of them
independently now instead of a single
neuron though i would like to have 27
neurons and i'll show you in a second
why i want 27 neurons
so instead of having just a 1 here which
is indicating this presence of one
single neuron
we can use 27
and then when w is 27 by 27
this will in parallel evaluate all the
27 neurons on all the 5 inputs
giving us a much better much much bigger
result so now what we've done is 5 by 27
multiplied 27 by 27
and the output of this is now 5 by 27
so we can see that the shape of this
is 5 by 27.
so what is every element here telling us
right
it's telling us for every one of 27
neurons that we created
what is the firing rate of those neurons
on every one of those five examples
so
the element for example 3 comma 13
is giving us the firing rate of the 13th
neuron
looking at the third input
and the way this was achieved is by a
dot product
between the third
input
and the 13th column
of this w matrix here
okay
so
using matrix multiplication we can very
efficiently evaluate
the dot product between lots of input
examples in a batch
and lots of neurons where all those
neurons have weights in the columns of
those w's
and in matrix multiplication we're just
doing those dot products and
in parallel just to show you that this
is the case we can take x and we can
take the third
row
and we can take the w and take its 13th
column
and then we can do
x and get three
elementwise multiply with w at 13.
and sum that up that's wx plus b
well there's no plus b it's just wx dot
product
and that's
this number
so you see that this is just being done
efficiently by the matrix multiplication
operation
for all the input examples and for all
the output neurons of this first layer
okay so we fed our 27-dimensional inputs
into a first layer of a neural net that
has 27 neurons right so we have 27
inputs and now we have 27 neurons these
neurons perform w times x they don't
have a bias and they don't have a
non-linearity like 10 h we're going to
leave them to be a linear layer
in addition to that we're not going to
have any other layers this is going to
be it it's just going to be
the dumbest smallest simplest neural net
which is just a single linear layer
and now i'd like to explain what i want
those 27 outputs to be
intuitively what we're trying to produce
here for every single input example is
we're trying to produce some kind of a
probability distribution for the next
character in a sequence
and there's 27 of them
but we have to come up with like precise
semantics for exactly how we're going to
interpret these 27 numbers that these
neurons take on
now intuitively
you see here that these numbers are
negative and some of them are positive
etc
and that's because these are coming out
of a neural net layer initialized with
these
normal distribution
parameters
but what we want is we want something
like we had here
like each row here
told us the counts and then we
normalized the counts to get
probabilities and we want something
similar to come out of the neural net
but what we just have right now is just
some negative and positive numbers
now we want those numbers to somehow
represent the probabilities for the next
character
but you see that probabilities they they
have a special structure they um
they're positive numbers and they sum to
one
and so that doesn't just come out of a
neural net
and then they can't be counts
because these counts are positive and
counts are integers
so counts are also not really a good
thing to output from a neural net
so instead what the neural net is going
to output and how we are going to
interpret the um
the 27 numbers is that these 27 numbers
are giving us log counts
basically
um
so instead of giving us counts directly
like in this table they're giving us log
counts
and to get the counts we're going to
take the log counts and we're going to
exponentiate them
now
exponentiation
takes the following form
it takes numbers
that are negative or they are positive
it takes the entire real line
and then if you plug in negative numbers
you're going to get e to the x
which is uh always below one
so you're getting numbers lower than one
and if you plug in numbers greater than
zero you're getting numbers greater than
one all the way growing to the infinity
and this here grows to zero
so basically we're going to
take these numbers
here
and
instead of them being positive and
negative and all over the place we're
going to interpret them as log counts
and then we're going to element wise
exponentiate these numbers
exponentiating them now gives us
something like this
and you see that these numbers now
because they went through an exponent
all the negative numbers turned into
numbers below 1 like 0.338 and all the
positive numbers originally turned into
even more positive numbers sort of
greater than one
so like for example
seven
is some positive number over here
that is greater than zero
but exponentiated outputs here
basically give us something that we can
use and interpret as the equivalent of
counts originally so you see these
counts here 112 7 51 1 etc
the neural net is kind of now predicting
uh
counts
and these counts are positive numbers
they can never be below zero so that
makes sense
and uh they can now take on various
values
depending on the settings of w
so let me break this down
we're going to interpret these to be the
log counts
in other words for this that is often
used is so-called logits
these are logits log counts
then these will be sort of the counts
largest exponentiated
and this is equivalent to the n matrix
sort of the n
array that we used previously remember
this was the n
this is the the array of counts
and each row here are the counts for the
for the um
next character sort of
so those are the counts and now the
probabilities are just the counts um
normalized
and so um
i'm not going to find the same but
basically i'm not going to scroll all
over the place
we've already done this we want to
counts that sum
along the first dimension and we want to
keep them as true
we've went over this and this is how we
normalize the rows of our counts matrix
to get our probabilities
props
so now these are the probabilities
and
these are the counts that we ask
currently and now when i show the
probabilities
you see that um
every row here
of course
will sum to 1
because they're normalized
and the shape of this
is 5 by 27
and so really what we've achieved is for
every one of our five examples
we now have a row that came out of a
neural net
and because of the transformations here
we made sure that this output of this
neural net now are probabilities or we
can interpret to be probabilities
so
our wx here gave us logits
and then we interpret those to be log
counts
we exponentiate to get something that
looks like counts
and then we normalize those counts to
get a probability distribution
and all of these are differentiable
operations
so what we've done now is we're taking
inputs we have differentiable operations
that we can back propagate through
and we're getting out probability
distributions
so
for example for the zeroth example that
fed in
right which was um
the zeroth example here was a one-half
vector of zero
and um
it basically corresponded to feeding in
this example here so we're feeding in a
dot into a neural net and the way we fed
the dot into a neural net is that we
first got its index
then we one hot encoded it
then it went into the neural net and out
came
this distribution of probabilities
and its shape
is 27 there's 27 numbers and we're going
to interpret this as the neural nets
assignment for how likely every one of
these characters um
the 27 characters are to come next
and as we tune the weights w
we're going to be of course getting
different probabilities out for any
character that you input
and so now the question is just can we
optimize and find a good w
such that the probabilities coming out
are pretty good and the way we measure
pretty good is by the loss function okay
so i organized everything into a single
summary so that hopefully it's a bit
more clear so it starts here
with an input data set
we have some inputs to the neural net
and we have some labels for the correct
next character in a sequence these are
integers
here i'm using uh torch generators now
so that you see the same numbers that i
see
and i'm generating um
27 neurons weights
and each neuron here receives 27 inputs
then here we're going to plug in all the
input examples x's into a neural net so
here this is a forward pass
first we have to encode all of the
inputs into one hot representations
so we have 27 classes we pass in these
integers and
x inc becomes a array that is 5 by 27
zeros except for a few ones
we then multiply this in the first layer
of a neural net to get logits
exponentiate the logits to get fake
counts sort of
and normalize these counts to get
probabilities
so we lock these last two lines by the
way here are called the softmax
which i pulled up here soft max is a
very often used layer in a neural net
that takes these z's which are logics
exponentiates them
and divides and normalizes it's a way of
taking
outputs of a neural net layer and these
these outputs can be positive or
negative
and it outputs probability distributions
it outputs something that is always
sums to one and are positive numbers
just like probabilities
um so it's kind of like a normalization
function if you want to think of it that
way and you can put it on top of any
other linear layer inside a neural net
and it basically makes a neural net
output probabilities that's very often
used and we used it as well here
so this is the forward pass and that's
how we made a neural net output
probability
now
you'll notice that
um
all of these
this entire forward pass is made up of
differentiable
layers everything here we can back
propagate through and we saw some of the
back propagation in micrograd
this is just
multiplication and addition all that's
happening here is just multiply and then
add and we know how to backpropagate
through them
exponentiation we know how to
backpropagate through
and then here we are summing
and sum is is easily backpropagable as
well
and division as well so everything here
is differentiable operation
and we can back propagate through
now we achieve these probabilities which
are 5 by 27
for every single example we have a
vector of probabilities that's into one
and then here i wrote a bunch of stuff
to sort of like break down uh the
examples
so we have five examples making up emma
right
and there are five bigrams inside emma
so bigram example a bigram example1 is
that e is the beginning character right
after dot
and the indexes for these are zero and
five
so then we feed in a zero
that's the input of the neural net
we get probabilities from the neural net
that are 27 numbers
and then the label is 5 because e
actually comes after dot
so that's the label
and then
we use this label 5 to index into the
probability distribution here
so
this
index 5 here is 0 1 2 3 4 5. it's this
number here
which is here
so that's basically the probability
assigned by the neural net to the actual
correct character
you see that the network currently
thinks that this next character that e
following dot is only one percent likely
which is of course not very good right
because this actually is a training
example and the network thinks this is
currently very very unlikely but that's
just because we didn't get very lucky in
generating a good setting of w so right
now this network things it says unlikely
and 0.01 is not a good outcome
so the log likelihood then is very
negative
and the negative log likelihood is very
positive
and so four is a very high negative log
likelihood and that means we're going to
have a high loss
because what is the loss the loss is
just the average negative log likelihood
so the second character is em
and you see here that also the network
thought that m following e is very
unlikely one percent
the for m following m i thought it was
two percent
and for a following m it actually
thought it was seven percent likely so
just by chance this one actually has a
pretty good probability and therefore
pretty low negative log likelihood
and finally here it thought this was one
percent likely
so overall our average negative log
likelihood which is the loss the total
loss that summarizes
basically the how well this network
currently works at least on this one
word not on the full data suggested one
word is 3.76 which is actually very
fairly high loss this is not a very good
setting of w's
now here's what we can do
we're currently getting 3.76
we can actually come here and we can
change our w we can resample it so let
me just add one to have a different seed
and then we get a different w
and then we can rerun this
and with this different c with this
different setting of w's we now get 3.37
so this is a much better w right and
that and it's better because the
probabilities just happen to come out
higher for the for the characters that
actually are next
and so you can imagine actually just
resampling this you know we can try two
so
okay this was not very good
let's try one more
we can try three
okay this was terrible setting because
we have a very high loss
so anyway i'm going to erase this
what i'm doing here which is just guess
and check of randomly assigning
parameters and seeing if the network is
good that is uh amateur hour that's not
how you optimize a neural net the way
you optimize your neural net is you
start with some random guess and we're
going to commit to this one even though
it's not very good
but now the big deal is we have a loss
function
so this loss
is made up only of differentiable
operations and we can minimize the loss
by tuning
ws
by computing the gradients of the loss
with respect to
these w matrices
and so then we can tune w to minimize
the loss and find a good setting of w
using gradient based optimization so
let's see how that will work now things
are actually going to look almost
identical to what we had with micrograd
so here
i pulled up the lecture from micrograd
the notebook it's from this repository
and when i scroll all the way to the end
where we left off with micrograd we had
something very very similar
we had
a number of input examples in this case
we had four input examples inside axis
and we had their targets these are
targets
just like here we have our axes now but
we have five of them and they're now
integers instead of vectors
but we're going to convert our integers
to vectors except our vectors will be 27
large instead of three large
and then here what we did is first we
did a forward pass where we ran a neural
net on all of the inputs
to get predictions
our neural net at the time this nfx was
a multi-layer perceptron
our neural net is going to look
different because our neural net is just
a single layer
single linear layer followed by a soft
max
so that's our neural net
and the loss here was the mean squared
error so we simply subtracted the
prediction from the ground truth and
squared it and summed it all up and that
was the loss and loss was the single
number that summarized the quality of
the neural net and when loss is low like
almost zero that means the neural net is
predicting correctly
so we had a single number that uh that
summarized the uh the performance of the
neural net and everything here was
differentiable and was stored in massive
compute graph
and then we iterated over all the
parameters we made sure that the
gradients are set to zero and we called
lost up backward
and lasted backward initiated back
propagation at the final output node of
loss
right so
yeah remember these expressions we had
loss all the way at the end we start
back propagation and we went all the way
back
and we made sure that we populated all
the parameters dot grad
so that graph started at zero but back
propagation filled it in
and then in the update we iterated over
all the parameters and we simply did a
parameter update where every single
element of our parameters was nudged in
the opposite direction of the gradient
and so we're going to do the exact same
thing here
so i'm going to pull this up
on the side here
so that we have it available and we're
actually going to do the exact same
thing so this was the forward pass so
where we did this
and probs is our wipe red so now we have
to evaluate the loss but we're not using
the mean squared error we're using the
negative log likelihood because we are
doing classification we're not doing
regression as it's called
so here we want to calculate loss
now the way we calculate it is it's just
this average negative log likelihood
now this probs here
has a shape of 5 by 27
and so to get all the we basically want
to pluck out the probabilities at the
correct indices here
so in particular because the labels are
stored here in array wise
basically what we're after is for the
first example we're looking at
probability of five right at index five
for the second example
at the the second row or row index one
we are interested in the probability
assigned to index 13.
at the second example we also have 13.
at the third row we want one
and then the last row which is four we
want zero so these are the probabilities
we're interested in right
and you can see that they're not amazing
as we saw above
so these are the probabilities we want
but we want like a more efficient way to
access these probabilities
not just listing them out in a tuple
like this so it turns out that the way
to do this in pytorch uh one of the ways
at least is we can basically pass in
all of these
sorry about that all of these um
integers in the vectors
so
the
these ones you see how they're just 0 1
2 3 4
we can actually create that using mp
not mp sorry torch dot range of 5
0 1 2 3 4.
so we can index here with torch.range of
and here we index with ys
and you see that that gives us
exactly these numbers
so that plucks out the probabilities of
that the neural network assigns to the
correct next character
now we take those probabilities and we
don't we actually look at the log
probability so we want to dot log
and then we want to just
average that up so take the mean of all
of that
and then it's the negative
average log likelihood that is the loss
so the loss here is 3.7 something and
you see that this loss 3.76 3.76 is
exactly as we've obtained before but
this is a vectorized form of that
expression
so
we get the same loss
and the same loss we can consider
service part of this forward pass
and we've achieved here now loss
okay so we made our way all the way to
loss we've defined the forward pass
we forwarded the network and the loss
now we're ready to do the backward pass
so backward pass
we want to first make sure that all the
gradients are reset so they're at zero
now in pytorch you can set the gradients
to be zero but you can also just set it
to none and setting it to none is more
efficient and pi torch will interpret
none as like a lack of a gradient and is
the same as zeros
so this is a way to set to zero the
gradient
and now we do lost it backward
before we do lost that backward we need
one more thing if you remember from
micrograd
pytorch actually requires
that we pass in requires grad is true
so that when we tell
pythorge that we are interested in
calculating gradients for this leaf
tensor by default this is false
so let me recalculate with that
and then set to none and lost that
backward
now something magical happened when
lasted backward was run
because pytorch just like micrograd when
we did the forward pass here
it keeps track of all the operations
under the hood it builds a full
computational graph just like the graphs
we've
produced in micrograd those graphs exist
inside pi torch
and so it knows all the dependencies and
all the mathematical operations of
everything
and when you then calculate the loss
we can call a dot backward on it
and that backward then fills in the
gradients of
all the intermediates
all the way back to w's which are the
parameters of our neural net so now we
can do w grad and we see that it has
structure there's stuff inside it
and these gradients
every single element here
so w dot shape is 27 by 27
w grad shape is the same 27 by 27
and every element of w that grad
is telling us
the influence of that weight on the loss
function
so for example this number all the way
here
if this element the zero zero element of
w
because the gradient is positive is
telling us that this has a positive
influence in the loss slightly nudging
w
slightly taking w 0 0
and
adding a small h to it
would increase the loss
mildly because this gradient is positive
some of these gradients are also
negative
so that's telling us about the gradient
information and we can use this gradient
information to update the weights of
this neural network so let's now do the
update it's going to be very similar to
what we had in micrograd we need no loop
over all the parameters because we only
have one parameter uh tensor and that is
w
so we simply do w dot data plus equals
uh the
we can actually copy this almost exactly
negative 0.1 times w dot grad
and that would be the update to the
tensor
so that updates
the tensor
and
because the tensor is updated we would
expect that now the loss should decrease
so
here if i print loss
that item
it was 3.76 right
so we've updated the w here so if i
recalculate forward pass
loss now should be slightly lower so
3.76 goes to
3.74
and then
we can again set to set grad to none and
backward
update
and now the parameters changed again
so if we recalculate the forward pass we
expect a lower loss again 3.72
okay and this is again doing the we're
now doing gradient descent
and when we achieve a low loss that will
mean that the network is assigning high
probabilities to the correctness
characters okay so i rearranged
everything and i put it all together
from scratch
so here is where we construct our data
set of bigrams
you see that we are still iterating only
on the first word emma
i'm going to change that in a second i
added a number that counts the number of
elements in x's so that we explicitly
see that number of examples is five
because currently we're just working
with emma and there's five backgrounds
there
and here i added a loop of exactly what
we had before so we had 10 iterations of
grainy descent of forward pass backward
pass and an update
and so running these two cells
initialization and gradient descent
gives us some improvement
on
the loss function
but now i want to use all the words
and there's not 5 but 228 000 bigrams
now
however this should require no
modification whatsoever everything
should just run because all the code we
wrote doesn't care if there's five
migrants or 228 000 bigrams and with
everything we should just work so
you see that this will just run
but now we are optimizing over the
entire training set of all the bigrams
and you see now that we are decreasing
very slightly so actually we can
probably afford a larger learning rate
and probably for even larger learning
rate
even 50 seems to work on this very very
simple example right so let me
re-initialize and let's run 100
iterations
see what happens
okay
we seem to be
coming up to some pretty good losses
here 2.47
let me run 100 more
what is the number that we expect by the
way in the loss we expect to get
something around what we had originally
actually
so all the way back if you remember in
the beginning of this video when we
optimized uh just by counting
our loss was roughly 2.47
after we had it smoothing
but before smoothing we had roughly 2.45
likelihood
sorry loss
and so that's actually roughly the
vicinity of what we expect to achieve
but before we achieved it by counting
and here we are achieving the roughly
the same result but with gradient based
optimization
so we come to about 2.4
6 2.45 etc
and that makes sense because
fundamentally we're not taking any
additional information we're still just
taking in the previous character and
trying to predict the next one but
instead of doing it explicitly by
counting and normalizing
we are doing it with gradient-based
learning and it just so happens that the
explicit approach happens to very well
optimize the loss function without any
need for a gradient based optimization
because the setup for bigram language
models are is so straightforward that's
so simple we can just afford to estimate
those probabilities directly and
maintain them
in a table
but the gradient-based approach is
significantly more flexible
so we've actually gained a lot
because
what we can do now is
we can expand this approach and
complexify the neural net so currently
we're just taking a single character and
feeding into a neural net and the neural
that's extremely simple but we're about
to iterate on this substantially we're
going to be taking multiple previous
characters and we're going to be feeding
feeding them into increasingly more
complex neural nets but fundamentally
out the output of the neural net will
always just be logics
and those logits will go through the
exact same transformation we are going
to take them through a soft max
calculate the loss function and the
negative log likelihood and do gradient
based optimization and so actually
as we complexify the neural nets and
work all the way up to transformers
none of this will really fundamentally
change none of this will fundamentally
change the only thing that will change
is
the way we do the forward pass where we
take in some previous characters and
calculate logits for the next character
in the sequence that will become more
complex
and uh but we'll use the same machinery
to optimize it
and um
it's not obvious how we would have
extended
this bigram approach
into the case where there are many more
characters at the input because
eventually these tables would get way
too large because there's way too many
combinations of what previous characters
could be
if you only have one previous character
we can just keep everything in a table
that counts but if you have the last 10
characters that are input we can't
actually keep everything in the table
anymore so this is fundamentally an
unscalable approach and the neural
network approach is significantly more
scalable and it's something that
actually we can improve on over time so
that's where we will be digging next i
wanted to point out two more things
number one
i want you to notice that
this
x ink here
this is made up of one hot vectors and
then those one hot vectors are
multiplied by this w matrix
and we think of this as multiple neurons
being forwarded in a fully connected
manner
but actually what's happening here is
that for example
if you have a one hot vector here that
has a one at say the fifth dimension
then because of the way the matrix
multiplication works
multiplying that one-half vector with w
actually ends up plucking out the fifth
row of w
log logits would become just the fifth
and that's because of the way the matrix
multiplication works
um
so
that's actually what ends up happening
so but that's actually exactly what
happened before
because remember all the way up here
we have a bigram we took the first
character and then that first character
indexed into a row of this array here
and that row gave us the probability
distribution for the next character so
the first character was used as a lookup
into a
matrix here to get the probability
distribution
well that's actually exactly what's
happening here because we're taking the
index we're encoding it as one hot and
multiplying it by w
so logics literally becomes
the
the appropriate row of w
and that gets just as before
exponentiated to create the counts
and then normalized and becomes
probability
so this w here
is literally
the same as this array here
but w remember is the log counts not the
counts so it's more precise to say that
w exponentiated
w dot x is this array
but this array was filled in by counting
and by
basically
populating the counts of bi-grams
whereas in the gradient-based framework
we initialize it randomly and then we
let the loss
guide us
to arrive at the exact same array
so this array exactly here
is
basically the array w at the end of
optimization except we arrived at it
piece by piece by following the loss
and that's why we also obtain the same
loss function at the end and the second
note is if i come here
remember the smoothing where we added
fake counts to our counts
in order to
smooth out and make more uniform the
distributions of these probabilities
and that prevented us from assigning
zero probability to
to any one bigram
now if i increase the count here
what's happening to the probability
as i increase the count probability
becomes more and more uniform
right because these counts go only up to
like 900 or whatever so if i'm adding
plus a million to every single number
here you can see how
the row and its probability then when we
divide is just going to become more and
more close to exactly even probability
uniform distribution
it turns out that the gradient based
framework has an equivalent to smoothing
in particular
think through these w's here
which we initialized randomly
we could also think about initializing
w's to be zero
if all the entries of w are zero
then you'll see that logits will become
all zero
and then exponentiating those logics
becomes all one
and then the probabilities turned out to
be exactly uniform
so basically when w's are all equal to
each other or say especially zero
then the probabilities come out
completely uniform
so
trying to incentivize w to be near zero
is basically equivalent to
label smoothing and the more you
incentivize that in the loss function
the more smooth distribution you're
going to achieve
so this brings us to something that's
called
regularization where we can actually
augment the loss function to have a
small component that we call a
regularization loss
in particular what we're going to do is
we can take w and we can for example
square all of its entries
and then we can um whoops
sorry about that
we can take all the entries of w and we
can sum them
and because we're squaring uh there will
be no signs anymore um
negatives and positives all get squashed
to be positive numbers
and then the way this works is you
achieve zero loss if w is exactly or
zero but if w has non-zero numbers you
accumulate loss
and so we can actually take this and we
can add it on here
so we can do something like loss plus
w square
dot sum
or let's actually instead of sum let's
take a mean because otherwise the sum
gets too large
so mean is like a little bit more
manageable
and then we have a regularization loss
here say 0.01 times
or something like that you can choose
the regularization strength
and then we can just optimize this and
now this optimization actually has two
components not only is it trying to make
all the probabilities work out but in
addition to that there's an additional
component that simultaneously tries to
make all w's be zero because if w's are
non-zero you feel a loss and so
minimizing this the only way to achieve
that is for w to be zero
and so you can think of this as adding
like a spring force or like a gravity
force that that pushes w to be zero so w
wants to be zero and the probabilities
want to be uniform but they also
simultaneously want to match up your
your probabilities as indicated by the
data
and so the strength of this
regularization is exactly controlling
the amount of counts
that you add here
adding a lot more counts
here
corresponds to
increasing this number
because the more you increase it the
more this part of the loss function
dominates this part and the more these
these weights will un be unable to grow
because as they grow
they uh accumulate way too much loss
and so if this is strong enough
then we are not able to overcome the
force of this loss and we will never
and basically everything will be uniform
predictions
so i thought that's kind of cool okay
and lastly before we wrap up
i wanted to show you how you would
sample from this neural net model
and i copy-pasted the sampling code from
before
where remember that we sampled five
times
and all we did we start at zero we
grabbed the current ix row of p and that
was our probability row
from which we sampled the next index and
just accumulated that and
break when zero
and running this
gave us these
results still have the
p in memory so this is fine
now
the speed doesn't come from the row of b
instead it comes from this neural net
first we take ix
and we encode it into a one hot row of x
inc
this x inc multiplies rw
which really just plucks out the row of
w corresponding to ix really that's
what's happening
and that gets our logits and then we
normalize those low jets
exponentiate to get counts and then
normalize to get uh the distribution and
then we can sample from the distribution
so if i run this
kind of anticlimactic or climatic
depending how you look at it but we get
the exact same result
um
and that's because this is in the
identical model not only does it achieve
the same loss
but
as i mentioned these are identical
models and this w is the log counts of
what we've estimated before but we came
to this answer in a very different way
and it's got a very different
interpretation but fundamentally this is
basically the same model and gives the
same samples here and so
that's kind of cool okay so we've
actually covered a lot of ground we
introduced the bigram character level
language model
we saw how we can train the model how we
can sample from the model and how we can
evaluate the quality of the model using
the negative log likelihood loss
and then we actually trained the model
in two completely different ways that
actually get the same result and the
same model
in the first way we just counted up the
frequency of all the bigrams and
normalized
in a second way we used the
negative log likelihood loss as a guide
to optimizing the counts matrix
or the counts array so that the loss is
minimized in the in a gradient-based
framework and we saw that both of them
give the same result
and
that's it
now the second one of these the
gradient-based framework is much more
flexible and right now our neural
network is super simple we're taking a
single previous character and we're
taking it through a single linear layer
to calculate the logits
this is about to complexify so in the
follow-up videos we're going to be
taking more and more of these characters
and we're going to be feeding them into
a neural net but this neural net will
still output the exact same thing the
neural net will output logits
and these logits will still be
normalized in the exact same way and all
the loss and everything else and the
gradient gradient-based framework
everything stays identical it's just
that this neural net will now complexify
all the way to transformers
so that's gonna be pretty awesome and
i'm looking forward to it for now bye